<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anti-Merlinus: or a confutation of Mr. William Lillies predictions for this year 1648. comprised in two bookes : one of which he cals Merlinus Anglicus, or An ephimeris : the other his Prognostication of the occurences in England, clearely proveing his predictions in both bookes to be groundlesse, absolutely void of art, full of contradictions, treason, falsehood, and such a ridiculous piece of foolery, as an artist would blush to owne, especially pretending (as he doth) to ground his predictions upon cacodemologie, or conference with devils, and lapsed angels, as well as on astrologie, an art lawfull and laudable. As also the authors own opinion, not only concerning what we may expect from the present treaty, and the principall occurences of the remaining part of this present year, but also his positive judgement touching the event and finall determination of this Civill War, succinctly set downe, together with his reasons in art therefore. / By H. Johnsen student in astrologie.</title>
            <author>Johnsen, H.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1171_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208821</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867743</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867743</idno>
            <idno type="VID">120066</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87589)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 120066)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 166:E1171[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anti-Merlinus: or a confutation of Mr. William Lillies predictions for this year 1648. comprised in two bookes : one of which he cals Merlinus Anglicus, or An ephimeris : the other his Prognostication of the occurences in England, clearely proveing his predictions in both bookes to be groundlesse, absolutely void of art, full of contradictions, treason, falsehood, and such a ridiculous piece of foolery, as an artist would blush to owne, especially pretending (as he doth) to ground his predictions upon cacodemologie, or conference with devils, and lapsed angels, as well as on astrologie, an art lawfull and laudable. As also the authors own opinion, not only concerning what we may expect from the present treaty, and the principall occurences of the remaining part of this present year, but also his positive judgement touching the event and finall determination of this Civill War, succinctly set downe, together with his reasons in art therefore. / By H. Johnsen student in astrologie.</title>
                  <author>Johnsen, H.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 55, [1] p. : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>A reply to: Lilly. William.  Merlini Anglici.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "[illegible] 21th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilly, William, 1602-1681. --  Merlini Anglici ephemeris.</term>
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:120066:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anti-Merlinus:</hi> OR A CONFVTATION of M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>William Lillies</hi> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions for this year 1648. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in two Bookes:</p>
            <p>One of which he cals <hi>Merlinus Anglicus,</hi> or <hi>An Ephimeris:</hi> The other his <hi>Prognoſtication</hi> of the Occurences in <hi>England,</hi> clearely prove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his predictions in both Bookes to be groundleſſe, abſolutely void of Art, full of contradictions, Treaſon, falſehood, and ſuch a ridiculous piece of foolery, as an Artiſt would bluſh to owne, eſpecially pretending (as he doth) to ground his predictions upon Cacodemolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, or conference with Devils, and lapſed Angels, as well as on Aſtrologie, an Art lawfull and laudable.</p>
            <p>As alſo the Authors own opinion, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerning what we may expect from the preſent Treaty, and the principall Occurences of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part of this preſent year, but alſo his poſitive judgement touching the event and finall determination of this Civill War, Succinctly ſet downe, together with his reaſons in Art therefore.</p>
            <p>By <hi>H. Johnſen</hi> Student in Aſtrologie.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:120066:2"/>
            <head>To His Highneſſe the <hi>PRINCE</hi> of <hi>VVALES.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Great Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat I approach ſo faire a ſhrine, with ſo coorſe an offering; accuſe not my unworthineſſe, but your owne worth which like the load-ſtar, is pleaſed to attract even the coorſeſt mettall, to make knowne its power. And indeed to whom elſe, <hi>(ſave to your Highneſſe)</hi> ſhould I Dedicate this <hi>worke</hi> of mine, ſith it was compiled <hi>for your dear Fathers ſake, my moſt Gracious Soveraigne?</hi> the neceſſity of the times even requiring it of me, as a teſtimony <hi>of my unfeigned love</hi> unto my native Country, and to its onely father, to whom 'tis turned <hi>Apoſtate</hi> yea a <hi>parricide.</hi> A taske in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>not of much labour, yet of exceeding danger,</hi> in ſuch times astheſe; I doubt not but your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe knowes full well, that <hi>but to ſpeake truth in England in theſe dayes,</hi> is now no leſſe then <hi>capitale crimen.</hi> I would therefore moſt willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if I could, have <hi>declined this taske,</hi> which I long forbore, expecting its <hi>performance,</hi> by ſome
<pb facs="tcp:120066:3"/>
               <hi>abler hand;</hi> but no man would eaſe me of that <hi>labour.</hi> I held it therefore my duty to my <hi>God,</hi> to my <hi>King,</hi> to my <hi>Country,</hi> to admoniſh all ſuch, who through miſguided <hi>zeale</hi> or otherwiſe, engaged againſt our <hi>Soveraigne,</hi> either in this or the former <hi>War,</hi> to repent betimes, and to make their ſpeedy attonement, both with the one, and the other: or elſe to let them know, that their <hi>deſtruction</hi> draweth nigh; that <hi>Aſtrologie</hi> is now cleare and poſitive therein; that Mr. <hi>William Lilly</hi> perſwading them to the contrary, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging them, with the aſſurance of ſucceſſe; is a falſe <hi>Prophet,</hi> all which I doubt not <hi>(God willing)</hi> but to prove ſo clearely by the rules of <hi>Art;</hi> and to confute him ſo manifeſtly, that any man (though but of indifferent capacity) ſhall be eaſily able to diſcerne his <hi>predictions,</hi> to be meere <hi>forgeries, lyes, and deluſions,</hi> mine to be grounded <hi>upon Art, and nature.</hi> Sir Chriſtopher Heiden, <hi>a famous Scholler of this Kingdome, in his defence of judiciall Aſtrologie,</hi> proves this <hi>Art</hi> to have been <hi>deduced from God to Adam, to Sheth, to Abraham,</hi> that in all Ages, <hi>Emperours, Kings, and men of the greateſt ranke,</hi> have not onely been favourors thereof, but <hi>Students</hi> alſo therein. I am therefore the more encouraged to preſent <hi>your. Highneſſe</hi> with a piece of this nature, not doubting but <hi>your Highneſſe</hi> will eaſily beleeve, that the <hi>Stars</hi> have influence upon all <hi>ſublunary bodies:</hi> doubtleſſe <hi>omniſcient God,</hi> never made
<pb facs="tcp:120066:3"/>any thing in vaine, and conſequently did not oreate, all thoſe <hi>glorious lampes of heaven,</hi> to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpangle the firmament: <hi>the Scripture tels us,</hi> that they were made for <hi>ſignes,</hi> and for <hi>tokens,</hi> and for <hi>dayes,</hi> and <hi>years;</hi> nay it goes further, and plainly affirmes, that the <hi>Stars in their courſe fought againſt Siſera;</hi> as I doubt not, <hi>but your Highneſſe</hi> ſhall perceive them to doe, againſt <hi>yours and the Kingdomes</hi> Enemies. I have ſtrong, yet humble <hi>hopes,</hi> (let them not be accounted <hi>preſumptions</hi>) that <hi>your Highneſſe</hi> will be <hi>graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly pleaſed,</hi> to give theſe my <hi>labours,</hi> an <hi>accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> anſwerable to the <hi>ambition,</hi> wherewith he offers them, who is,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſe moſt obſequious and ready ſervant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:120066:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Strologie</hi> is an Art I love, and I may lawfully do ſo: <hi>Cacodemologie</hi> I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely hate, for all men ought to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor it. I liſt not mith <hi>Mr. Lilly,</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into the <hi>name, nature, or potency</hi> of the <hi>guardian Angel</hi> of this, or any other <hi>Kingdome</hi> in the <hi>Univerſe,</hi> nor care I to know, whether he be active, or a ſluggard. <hi>This</hi> is to taſte of that forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruite, wherewith our <hi>grand Parents</hi> teeth were ſet on edge: for my part, I had rather know nothing at all, then by unlawfull Arts. <hi>Were</hi> there not a lawfull Art, whereby a man might foreſee future accidents, I ſhould never deſire an ability to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict any thing. <hi>That Aſtrology</hi> is an Art lawfull enough, there is no man that is <hi>compos mentis,</hi> will I thinke deny; and the validity thereof, I dare maintaine againſt all opponents, and yet that is a crabbed learning I will not deny. I am verily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, and that not without cauſe, that the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> himſelfe, knnowes very little of future accidents, otherwiſe, or further, then he finds them legible, in the <hi>aſpects, and configurations of that ſtarry vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:120066:4"/>of heaeven, why then ſhould any man be ſo curious, nay ſo madde as to deſire to know that by the <hi>Devill,</hi> which he himſelfe may know without him, and lawfully from the ſame Art? I deny not, but the Devil is the ſubtileſt Aſtrologian in the world; his angelicall nature, and long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience muſt needs perſwade us thereunto: but is be not withall the father of lies? the <hi>word of God</hi> affirmes him ſo to be, and <hi>Mr. Lillies predictions</hi> for this year confirmes it; for if it be poſſible they out-doe the Devill himſelfe for lying: ſuch a ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous piece of folly, foolery, and contradictions, an <hi>artiſt</hi> would bluſh to owne. It is his owne axiome, and a very good one, that <hi>qui inter multa falſa, pauca miſcet vera, non eſt ei in recitando dicta ejus, quicquam tribuendum:</hi> he that lies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, and ſpeakes, or writes, but now and then, a truth, is neither to be truſted, nor to be beleeved. I ſhall eaſily aſſent to <hi>Mr. Lilly,</hi> calling ſuch <hi>Malignant Prophets,</hi> with this <hi>axiome</hi> he laſhes <hi>Mr. Wharton,</hi> for one onely miſtake, and that a ſmall one too; I meane comparatively ſmall, in regard of his owne <hi>folio</hi> failings: for the ſubſtance of what <hi>Mr. Wharton</hi> predicted, was doubtleſſe true; and <hi>Mr. Lilly</hi> will find it ſo to be, and to his coſt I feare. <hi>Upon the Conjunction with</hi> Saturne <hi>and</hi> Mars, <hi>in the eighth houſe, near oculus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> he predicted the utter overthrow of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: thus far I am confident he was right enough, but the time of this their overthrow he aſſigned, to
<pb facs="tcp:120066:5"/>be about the end of <hi>June</hi> laſt; and in this he failed I muſt confeſſe: nor had he reaſon to affirme it, for the <hi>Conjunction of thoſe two Planets,</hi> was but then newly paſt; did not yet begin to operate; their effects continue many <hi>moneths:</hi> and long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the effects of that <hi>Conjunction ceaſe; the Moone comes to be Eclipſed, and in Gemini too, near the body of Saturne, in the ſeaventh and eighth houſes of heaven;</hi> and if this doe not totally overthrow them (provided that the King and they agree not before, by a Perſonall Treaty) I ſhall for ever after queſtion the truth of that Art, which I ſo much love: the validity whereof, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet found cauſe to doubt of. <hi>At</hi> leaſt I ſhall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly queſtion, my owne judgement therein: the greateſt fury &amp; force, both of the Conjunction, &amp; the Eclipſe alſo, will be over by the <hi>end of June</hi> next; and therefore my hopes are ſtrong, and <hi>my grounds in Art I am ſure are good;</hi> that by that time, moſt of our troubles wil be overblown; <hi>yet perhaps not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ended,</hi> for ſome few moneths following. <hi>For this ſo ſmall a miſtake in Mr. Wharton,</hi> he cals him <hi>Malignant Prophet, the</hi> ſcorne of Art, change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, &amp;c. but <hi>qui alterum incuſat probri ipſum ſe intueri oportet,</hi> he that is ſo buſie to pick holes in the coates of others, had need have more then an or dinary care of his owne words and actions. <hi>M. Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies axiome could not reach Mr. Wharton;</hi> for he committed not many, but one; not a groſſe, but a ſmall miſtake; I ſay <hi>comparatively ſmall,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb facs="tcp:120066:5"/>of thoſe <hi>grand falſehoods,</hi> thoſe almoſt <hi>innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable contradictions,</hi> thoſe many <hi>Treaſons,</hi> and <hi>forgeries,</hi> committed to the <hi>Preſſe</hi> this year, <hi>by Merlinus Anglicus.</hi> I will here give you but a glimpſe of his <hi>failings and feignings</hi> this year, anon I ſhall ſet them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>out in more lively colours; and <hi>marſhall</hi> them together, and as near as I can, into ranke and file. Did he not in divers places of his <hi>Ephimeris predict peace this year? and abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely affirme, that</hi> this would be a year of <hi>joy, and merryment, not of Martiall exploits,</hi> in this our Kingdome? <hi>Nay did he not baſely, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litiouſly, ſcandalize Mr.</hi> Wharton, <hi>for predicting War?</hi> whither ſpake true? yet <hi>Mr. Lilly</hi> cals him <hi>manapian Aſtrologer;</hi> and this <hi>Utopian,</hi> and <hi>malignant Aſtrologie.</hi> Did not <hi>Mr. Lilly</hi> affirme, yea confidently alſo, that the <hi>Scots</hi> would not aſſiſt the <hi>King this year againſt the Parliament?</hi> no nor any other <hi>Kingdome</hi> elſe? <hi>he ſaith, behold the Scots are honourable, and have no invaſive de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne againſt us:</hi> nay, he ſaieth farther, <hi>that they, who are of this opinion, that the Scots wil invade us, have no eies:</hi> I ſhal willingly leave it to the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> judgement, who deſerves moſt to ride <hi>blind bayard. He addes</hi> afterwards, that he can ſpeake no evill of the <hi>Scottiſh Nation,</hi> ſith the <hi>heavens</hi> give him no information; but after he hard that they were come, contrary to his <hi>prediction,</hi> he could ſcarce invent any <hi>Oyſter-whore language,</hi> bad enough to revile them with. <hi>Againe</hi> he ſaith, that
<pb facs="tcp:120066:6"/>ſome thinke that the <hi>Parliament Souldiers, will ſome of them diſſert the cauſe,</hi> and fight <hi>Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head againſt Round-head, Citizen againſt Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen; which yet he affirmes will not come to paſſe:</hi> and yet we all know, this and more was true enough; <hi>Ergo,</hi> Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> ſaid falſe, and therefore is no ſon of <hi>Merlins:</hi> Is not I pray the <hi>Fleet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volted to the Prince?</hi> have there been no <hi>knocks at all this year in London?</hi> is not this Round-head againſt Round-head, Citizen againſt Citizen? <hi>He ſaith of Ireland,</hi> that this year, there will be in that <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ſuch notorious, and ſo great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions; ſuch fierce and cruel Wars, that of their ſufferings, they, and their Children ſhall know no end. Loe, they are quiet in that Kingdome; no ſuch thing at all hath hapned. Very little Blood (if any at all) hath been ſhed in that place: behold, they are willing, yea, and ready alſo to aſſiſt His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, our moſt gracious Soveraigne. <hi>It ſeemes</hi> this year, that his fancy was overburthened <hi>(as himſelf confeſſeth) with very intricate meditations;</hi> fine white and yellow meditations: doubtleſſe the <hi>Parliament</hi> caſh which he hath got, for a reward of his Treaſon and Treachery, has had ſtrong influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon his giddy crown, to fill it, with ſuch ſtrange Chymeraes: and certainly it were madneſſe in any, to belch out ſuch horrid Treaſons againſt his <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne:</hi> ſuch encomiums to his enemies, the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents,</hi> and their Army, who have not onely
<pb facs="tcp:120066:6"/>rob'd their gracious <hi>Soveraigne</hi> of His native brithright, revil'd His wife, and Children, with moſt foule and falſe aſperſions; but have Impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and enſlav'd His perſon alſo; ſlaine and rob'd His Loyall Subjects, ſet all His Kingdomes on a flame; if he were not well rewarded by his great Maſters, for ſo great Treaſon: It is now well knowne to all men, that have eyes to diſtinguiſh chalke from cheeſe, white from black, light from darkeneſſe, that their intentions, (not withſtanding their faire pretences for the Kings Honour, the ſubjects Liberty, and the reformation of Religion) have beene ſolely to enſlave their Soveraigne, to raign themſelves, and like <hi>Phenixes,</hi> to revive their bankerupt fortunes, out of the Kingdomes ruines: and how far they have accompliſh'd theſe their aimes, there is no diſcreet, and honeſt man in this whole Kingdome, but evidently now perceives: how have they pillaged, rob'd, and plundered the whole Kingdome? to what vaſt ſummes, have they raiſed their owne tottering fortunes? how have they preferred to places of higheſt truſt, and greateſt gaine, ſuch as have ſtoutly endeavoured to raiſe them to this height, either by ſword or penne? this undeniable poſition being granted, as perforce it must; it will alſo follow, that <hi>Mr. William Lilly</hi> deſerves the Van, in this liſt of <hi>Traytors,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently hath been therefore well rewarded. For doubtleſſe <hi>Fairfax and Cromwell,</hi> could hardly have led the Kingdome by the noſe thus long, had
<pb facs="tcp:120066:7"/>not <hi>Merlinus Anglicus, that Welchified, London, Incubus,</hi> entered the ſceane, and prevailed as much, upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the minds of giddy-headed men, with his ſcreech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owles quill, as they upon their bodies, with all their Armies, Engines, Weapons, and ſubtile machinations. For people are, and were ever too to apt to be ſeduced by any, who but pretend to <hi>Aſtrologie, Aecroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Chyromancy:</hi> eſpecially if they tell them that the things they predict are from God, or revealed by ſome Angel, they will eaſily beleeve almoſt whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſuch a one ſhall aſſert: for bring them but once to beleeve, that there is validity in the Art, and learning in the <hi>Artiſt,</hi> they come on of their owne accords, to beleeve what ſuch an Artiſt affirmes to be true, and infallibly to happen: although 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that the ſtars doe but encline, cannot enforce. And moſt men loving preferment, and eſtate in this world, more then their God, or their <hi>King, the Lords Anointed,</hi> will eaſily make ſhipwrack of their duty to the one, of their Allegiance to the other; if once they beleeve they ſhall be looſers by either. <hi>They will argue thus:</hi> whatſoever God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, ſhall come to paſſe, cannot be avoided by any induſtry of man; nay it were madneſſe in any to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt it, and loſt labour if he did, but <hi>Mr. Lilly</hi> hath affirmed, and with a <hi>ſic eſt in fatis;</hi> that the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall overcome the <hi>King,</hi> and His ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, and therefore it were madneſſe in them, to caſt away their deareſt lives, and their estates to boote, in the <hi>Kings</hi> quarrell, ſith all is but loſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:120066:7"/>
            <p>Thus have many a thouſand in this Kingdome been hobgoblin'd into Rebellion, againſt their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soveraigne. <hi>If this will not prevaile, he hath yet another baite for the devouter ſort of men: he ſaith, that the Parliament and Army are Gods I nſtruments,</hi> Ergo. <hi>ſaith he, (and they believe it to excellent logick, yea, and very good divinity too) you ought to adhere to the Parliament, and not affront them, as of late.</hi> A ſpeciall concluding argument indeed; but good M. <hi>Lilly,</hi> is not the Divell too Gods Inſtrument? makes not God ſometimes uſe of him, as we do of a Hang-man to execute his pleaſure? muſt we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore adhere to the Devill? no certainly. I cannot ſufficiently wonder at the madneſſe of men, in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering themſelves to be ſo long deluded, by meere falſe ſhoods and forgeries; even ſuch as are to be diſcerned by every eye, if they wink not on purpoſe; but this was alwayes the faſhion of the world, to believe falſehood eaſily; hardly to believe the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tunc etiam fatis aperit Caſſandra futuris</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ora dei juſſa, non unquam credita Teucris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that the Kingdome may be no longer deluded by ſuch a <hi>cheating ſycophant:</hi> I am reſolved to enter the Liſts, againſt this <hi>demigorgon, this hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent fury, our junior Merlin:</hi> not doubting, but to confute his ſophiſtry by reaſon; his Aſtrologie, by Aſtrologie, his Cacodemology, by the word of God; and by that time I have throughly uncaſed him,
<pb facs="tcp:120066:8"/>I doubt not, but he will appear to all the World, more ridiculous then the <hi>Apes of India,</hi> that mockt the <hi>Macedonian Army.</hi> I deſire not to derogate any thing from M. <hi>Lillies</hi> abilitie in the art of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy;</hi> I am verily perſwaded, that he is a good proficient therein; and underſtands rightly, a great part thereof: but he that wilfully, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely ſhuts his eyes, that he may not ſee, deſerves to be laſht with many ſtripes. I proteſt ingenuouſly, I never had any intentions of ſhewing my ſelf in Print, upon this ſubject, till I ſaw M. <hi>Lillies Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meris</hi> for this year, which was not till <hi>June:</hi> and then I was in a manner compelled to this taske, for either I muſt write a confutation, or ſome body elſe; or elſe the Kingdome muſt be ſtill deluded, gull'd, and cheated with forgeries and lies: and <hi>Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> (an art which I extreamly love) be condemn'd therefore. Before I had fully perfected my confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his <hi>Ephemeris,</hi> he puts forth his judgement upon the <hi>parelii; and the conjunction of Saturne and Mars:</hi> which, as ſoone as I had peruſed, I found it ſo full of Contradictions, Treaſon, Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and ſuch a ridiculous piece of foppery; as the eye of man, nor that greater of the world, ſcarce ever yet beheld, which made me conclude, that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Lilly</hi> had now even ſold himſelf to work wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe, which put me on to write a Confutation of both his ſaid Bookes, with all the ſpeed I could. In the doing of which, it cannot be expected, but that he vaunting ſo much as he doth, of his own abilities;
<pb facs="tcp:120066:8"/>as to call thoſe who contradict him, <hi>Manapian A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers, the ſcorne of Art, Changelings, &amp;c.</hi> that when I finde him tripping, I ſhould bite him a little with my cynick tooth: when I finde him feighning, or failing, if I laſh him ſoundly with my Satyrs whip. My Love to my <hi>Country,</hi> my Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to my <hi>Soveraign,</hi> my Reſpect to <hi>Art,</hi> and my juſt deteſtation of all ſuch <hi>vaunting and Machivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Traitors,</hi> challenge of me, and muſt receive from me, no leſſe, no lower ſatisfaction: I had no other ſiniſter motives to induce me thereunto; as hatred, malice, envie, &amp;c. and ſo he unfeignedly proteſteth, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in his beſt endeavours, H. I.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:120066:9"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:120066:9"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough the dire influence, of that prodigious Comer, in 16.18 (ſo fatall to <hi>Germany, Spaine, Ireland, England,</hi> and moſt Kingdomes in Europe) be now by the divine permiſſion of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, tranſmitted, beyond our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Horizon, to go viſit ſome remoter clymates, yet we have ſtill (ſaith Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi>) the diſtempered effects of the parelij or 3 Suns viſible in <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> Aprill the 3d. 1647/8 forcibly operating and not determined. We are ſubject I am ſure at preſent to the influence of the ſquare of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> and <hi>Iupiter</hi> imminent the 29 or March laſt, upon the 9 of March laſt, the ſun entred <hi>Aries:</hi> Upon the 10th. of June laſt, the ſun entred <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> Upon the 28 of June, there hapned a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars:</hi> Upon the 12th. of September, the ſun encred <hi>Libra:</hi> Upon the 20 of November there hapneth an Eclipſe of the Moone, and upon the 11. of <hi>December,</hi> the Sun enters Capricorne. The 3. foremoſt. and only thoſe Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> makes uſe of, in his Ephimeris for this yeare, but in his book called an <hi>aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prediction,</hi> of the occurrences of <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:120066:10"/>he adds the Conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> from theſe as from his <hi>baſis,</hi> he extracts his Iudg. ment for this yeare he conſiders not at all, the ſuns ingreſſe into <hi>Cancer, Libra and Capricorne</hi> notwithſtanding the aſcendant of the Suns ingreſs into <hi>Aries,</hi> be a moveable ſigne, yea, and the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter degrees thereof, and therefore cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſignifie the actions, of above one quarter of a yeare, as moſt, (and let him produce any good Author to the contrary, I will yeeld him the bucklers without further diſpute) Nor yetdoth he conſider, the eclipſe of the Moon, I ſhall from the ail as for my <hi>baſis,</hi> and ground worke, extract my Judgment of thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r;</hi> And ſo Mr. <hi>Lily</hi> ought to have done, had he deſired to have enformed either himſelfe, or his Reader right. Nay Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> himſelfe imputes this as a fault to M. <hi>Whar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> upbraiding him, that he fetcht his hotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potch Oracles, with which he ſo deluded the people, meerly from the Coniunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> whereas every one ought he ſaith to conſider the ſuns ingreſſe, into the 4. Cardinall points, with all the remarkable conjunctions, and aſpects of the year, the moſt materiall whereof, he himſelfe omitteth, and ſo becomes guilty of that himſelfe which he ſo much taxeth in others: I deſire therefore, it may be put to the vote, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he deſervs not to be laſht with the ſelf ſame whip, which he prepared for them.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:120066:10"/>
            <figure>
               <head>Binorum Pareſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Feb. 28. 1647/48</head>
            </figure>
            <p>There is hardly any one thing amrmed, by any Author, de parelijs, which is not again contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, by ſome other author: it will be a matter therefore of great difficulty for me, or any man elſe, amongſt ſo many different opinions to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh truth from falſhood, and conſequently to give any certaine judgmement, of theſe parelij or falſe Suns, ſeen in <hi>Lancaſhire</hi> as Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: <hi>I</hi> ſaw them not my ſelfe, but doubtleſſe ſuch mock. Suns do ſometimes appeare; though there are ſome that will hardly grant it, yea, do ſtoutly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:120066:11"/>deny it, whither they proceed from a natural cauſe, or whether they be miraculous, I will not dispute: nor what the matter is, of which they are made; but it is a very materiall quaere, and worthy to be reſolved, whether they proceed from naturall cauſes, or be miraculouſly framed by <hi>Angells,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> aſſerteth. For if they proceed from naturall cauſes, 'tis then probable, that they ſignifie nothing but weather, if other. wiſe, then doubtles their ſigniſication is great, and of a much larger extent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> will not contend with Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> in this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, becauſe tis diſputable: It ſhall be my care, not to juſtle with him, till <hi>I</hi> be ſure to foile him. Theſe parelij, appeare moſt in Northren clymats, commonly in the morning, the Son being neare the horizon; their motion is alwayes with the Sun, and they ever keep the ſame diſtance from him: their continuance is very ſhort, ſeldome a bove an houre and a quarter at moſt.</p>
            <p>Many Authors do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſly deny theſe parelij, to have any other ſignification, then upon weather: ſome contend ſtoutly that they have: Amongſt ſo many different, and indeed contrary opinions, it will be dub ous what to affirme: but doubt, leſſe the beſt way will be, to imitate nature, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving ſuch Riddles: I will therefore cull out, from Mr. <hi>Lillies</hi> collections, ſuch aphoriſmes, as are likeſt to be true; and then from them all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract a judgement.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:120066:11"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Parelij ſunt monitores de inſidij, et conſilije clandeſtinis, quae ineuntur adverſus eos, qui in magno ſplendore dignitatis rerum potiuntur.</hi> Thus in Engliſh; parelij or mock Suns do admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh of treacheries, and <hi>Clandeſtine</hi> counſells a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt men of great dignity: had it ſaid thus, <hi>I</hi> ſhould have lik't it better, and queſtionleſſe it had bin truer: they are Monitors of treacherous plots, and <hi>Clandeſtine</hi> counſells, againſt ſome King, or Prince, by ſuch as would dethrone him, or make him away, for without doubt a true Sun, ſignifies a lawfull King, a mock Sun, an uſurper. and this will clearly appear by the ſecond.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Diverſa parelia Regni eiuſdem guberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores fere diverſes, aut viros fere Principes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentant; circulus autem regni partes, aut ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitates: verus ille Sol circuli medio, perſonan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> regiam, apta ſimilitudine monſtrat Gem:</hi> Divers or many parelij, repreſent the Governours of the ſame Kingdome, to be many: or they perſonate men of almoſt princely rank, or like Princes: the true ſun in the midd le of the circle, declares byan apt compariſon, a regall perſon, of the ſame King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: the Circle about the ſuns ſhew the parts or Cities of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Cum fictiſoles, veluti ſatellites, verum ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem cingunt, tunc in captivit atem cadunt ſummi Reges.</hi> When mock ſuns like Yeomen of the Gard, do encompaſſe the true Sun, then greateſt Princes, ſhall fall into captivity.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:120066:12"/>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Tres ſoles, triumvir at us eſſe ſigna, et ſuo tempore ſignificaſſe imperia, Caroli quinti Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaris, Henrici ſecundi Gallorum Regis, et Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani Turcarum Sultani aſſerit Cardanus</hi> 3. Suns Signifie honour to be conferred on three, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deſerving men, and in his time did ſignifie, the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th. <hi>Henry</hi> the 2d. King of <hi>France,</hi> and of <hi>Solimon Sultan,</hi> or Emperour of <hi>Turkie.</hi> But I like very little of this Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme, nor is it likely to be true: for the mock. ſuns cannot ſignifie deſerving men, nor ſhall ſuch ever poſſeſſe that Kingdome they expect, becauſe they quickly vaniſh, and leave the true Sun in poſſeſsion: though they beſiege him, and impriſon him for a time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hi statum mundi ſibi ſubiectum indicaus, non in futurum, ſed de die preſente: indicant autens ſchiſmata, et ſimilia, reſque ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>irandas, et rare ſier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſolitas: praecipue autens evidentia deliria ac indicantur, et conatus ſtulti ſuperiorum, it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſicut Duos ſoles exiſtere ſuperfluum eſt, it a ſuperfluum est quod illi indicant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe parelij, intimate the ſtate of the world, ſubject unto them, what ſhall preſently, not long after ſucceed: they foreſhew Schiſmes &amp;c. won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull matters, and ſuch as are ſeldome uſed to be done, eſpecially evident madneſſe, and the foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh endeavours of great men: ſo that as there is no neceſſity of 3 Suns ſo there is no need of ſuch things as they ſignifie,</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:120066:12"/>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Parelius aquas, aut ventos promittit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paulus</hi> the <hi>Minerva</hi> a mock Sun ſignifies, raine or a tempeſt.</p>
            <p>The ſigniſication of the Parelij, ſeemes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be this. A ſun whither true or falſe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a King: a true Sun, a lawfull King: a mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſun, an uſurper, or one that would be a King: here are two mock ſuns. there are therefore two that would be Kings, perhaps <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and <hi>Cromwell,</hi> falſe ſuns, admoniſh, of Treaſon, and treachery to be performed by the mock-ſuns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their lawfull Soveraign, whom they would either dethrone, or make away, have already impriſoned, as appears by the mock ſuns encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing the true. Certainly theſe mock. ſuns which inviron the true ſun, muſt ſignifie the Parliament and army, or if you will the Presbyterian and the Independent: Theſe mock ſuns, ſignifie Treaſons Treacheries. Schiſmes, Hereſies, and clandeſtine councells, then acting againſt the true Sun.</p>
            <p>But as it is a ſuperfluous thing to have two or 3 ſuns: ſo is that wich they go about, that is, play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King Catchers. Though they ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it, yet ſhall they never come to be Kings [to the Halter they may] for the mock Sunnes ſuddainly vaniſh, leaving the true ſun ſhining in the firmament, &amp; at laſt free from confinement, whence <hi>I</hi> gather, that his Majeſty ſhall com at length out of priſon, and that whoſoever deſires to weare his Diadem, ſhall go without it: for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:120066:13"/>the mock ſuns quickly vaniſhed, they ſhall never therefore obtain their aime.</p>
            <p>The Eclipſe of the <hi>Moon,</hi> in November next in <hi>Gemini</hi> will ſoon after without all queſtion, baniſh the Parelij, or mock ſuns into the land of darkneſſe, What think you Mr <hi>Lilly,</hi> is not this the naturall explication of our parelij?</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> would have the true ſun to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie the Parliament, and the mock ſuns their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers, and his reaſon ['tis <hi>judicium ſine judici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>] is becauſe theſe was at the time of the appearance or the pare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>j, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oe vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> face of authority, but what was in them, what then? the authority is the Kings, <hi>de jure,</hi> though theirs <hi>de facto.</hi> The Parliament was not impriſoned, the true Son was invironed by the mock ſuns, <hi>ergo</hi> the true ſun ſignifies the King, a the Parliament is excellent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and moſt ſignificantly repreſented by the mock ſuns invironing the true, for they keep him priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner &amp;c, that they might make uſe or his power, and Authority. Let any indifferent man judge between us,<note place="margin">Here ſhould have bin inferred a Scheame for the time of the appearance of the Pare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lij</note> and let the Golden ball be give to him who hits the truth.</p>
            <p>This Scheme which was ſet at the the time of the appearance of the parelij, were it exactly don as I much doubt it was not: it were ſuperfluous to judge it; but yet let Mr Lilly ſay what he will, this very Scheme is ten times more for the King then for the Parliament, nay <hi>Mr. Lilly</hi> himſelf though at unawares confeſſeth as much in theſe,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:120066:13"/>words: <hi>Yet this of neceſsity will follow, either an amendment, or a complyance, of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers themſelves, or a finall revolt of the People from them. Teſtimonium tunm quod in aliena re leve eſt hoc contrate grave eſt.</hi> The Moone who ſignifies the people, oppoſeth both the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant, and the Sun their ſignificator, and after her ſeparation from the oppoſition of <hi>Sol,</hi> ſnee applyes forcibly to the trine of <hi>Saturn,</hi> Lord of the 11. in the 2. and this muſt needes ſignifie, victory to the King, although the tayle of the <hi>Dragon,</hi> be in the 10th. houſe: for that ſignifies only ſcandalls, falls, and ſome danger by poyſon to the King, Jupiter Lord of the aſcendant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trograde, hurts the Parliament more, then the King, for he opoſes the aſcendant, there are many therefore of the Parliament men, who will be for the King againſt the Parliament. The Moone in oppoſition to the ſun, both well fortified in angles, argues a defection of moſt of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, from them, and their adherance to the King, in regard the Moone applyes immediately after her ſeparation, to <hi>Saturn</hi> our freind in the ſecond.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> affirmeth, that the King decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in honour, even ſince the appearance of the mock-ſuns in 1644. and doubtleſſe he would have him decline worſe ſtill upon the appearance of theſe new mock-ſuns: but ſee how ridiculous he makes himſelſe: there is no Artiſt but knowes
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:120066:14"/>that it was the Comet in 1618. and the great conjunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſe of the Sun in 1639. which brought his Majeſty ſo low. And the conjunction of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in Gemini, in the 8th. houſe, near <hi>Ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Tauri,</hi> and the Moon Eclipſed in the 7th. and the 8th. houſes, in <hi>Gemini,</hi> near the body of <hi>Saturne,</hi> will bring the Parliament lower.</p>
            <p>The figure of the Suns ingreſſe into <hi>Aries</hi> for the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Here are 3. Shemes wanting the firſt; for the Suns in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe into Aries 9. Martij, the ſecond for the ſquare of Saturne and Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 29 Martij, the third for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of th Sun and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rne, 16. Maij.</note> hath 26. degrees and 50. minuts, of <hi>Libra</hi> aſcending which ſigne in regard it is moveable, cauſeth, that this Scheme, ſhall ſignifie unto us, the actions but of one quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this yeare, eſpecially there being ſo few degrees thereof in the Aſcendent, and this is the unanimous opinion, of all the learned in this art, although Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> thinking it fitteſt for his purpoſe, would needs perſwade us to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and would have it ſerve for the whole yeare: but even reaſon it ſelfe would perſwade us. (had the learned bin ſilent herein) that the fag end of a moveable ſign aſcending, there is no great heed or truſt to be had to ſuch a figure: and yet for this quarter, it muſt direct us. viz. Vntill the Sun enrers the ſigne <hi>Cancer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as much as the aſcending ſigne is moveable, doubtleſſe a great change, of humane affaires ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proacheth, concerning the Rites. Priviledges, Lawes, and Cuſtomes, of this Kingdome, <hi>ſi cute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra concenſerint, as here they do.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:120066:14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Venus</hi> is Lady of the aſccnding ſigne, but <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> hath more dignities therein, <hi>viz.</hi> his exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and triplicity, neither of them have much to do in the Aſcendent, as the caſe ſtands; for in regard there are ſo ſew degree, of <hi>Libra</hi> in the aſcendent, they quickly leave their rule to <hi>Mars,</hi> and then the dominion of the ſucceeding part of the year, is in a manner wholly committed unto <hi>Mars;</hi> not ſo much becauſe he governs the ſigne <hi>Scorpio,</hi> intercepted in the aſcendent, at the time of the vernal-ingres, (as Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> would have it) but becauſe he is the principall Planet, in moſt of the lunations, and remarkable Aſpects, happening this year. <hi>Clandeſtine</hi> practiſes ſhall therefore now faile, and deeds of Armes be very frequent, in many parts of this Kingdome. Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> cryes peace; but to our coſts we have, and ſhall find, that we ſhall not enjoy the ſettled conditon, he promiſeth; this year will not produce it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Si Mars fuerit Dominus anni, directus et non aſpexerit Aſcendentem, fignificat plurimas com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtiones et nocumentum ab ignibus, et agritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, quae advenient hominibus cauſa ſangninis et deſtructionem vegitabilium, cauſa valetudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis ventorum.</hi> If <hi>Mars</hi> be Lord of the year, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect, and behold not the aſcendent, it ſignifies much burnings, and hurts by fire, many diſeaſes in men, cauſed by peccant blood: and deſtruction of vegitables, by the grcatneſſe of winds.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Plenilunium</hi> preventionall he is in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:120066:15"/>11th. houſe, in conjunction with <hi>Mer.</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Moone, this ſignifies great enmity amongſt freinds, Conſumption of much treaſure, his poſation in the revelation in the fifth, denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth much Fornication, Adultery, and Mortality in the Southren parts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturn</hi> in the 8. houſe ſignifies much detriment, and loſſe to the place, which is ſubject to that ſigne he is in, tribulation, anguiſh, and many contentions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturn is</hi> in <hi>porigeo,</hi> as near the earth as he can be, and meets with <hi>Mars</hi> in <hi>Gemini,</hi> where there are many ſtars of contrary nature; this, but not only this, was the cauſe of the wetneſſe and cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the yeare. The <hi>Parelij</hi> alſo, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and foreſhew the ſame, for <hi>Parelius ventos aut pluvias promittit,</hi> there are alſo ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſons in art therefore, as you ſhall heare anon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luna in quartain ſigno infor tunato, erit populu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fortiter obſeſſus, et accident ei carceres, et anxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etates graves,</hi> The Moon in the 4th. houſe, in an unfortunate ſign, ſignifies that the people ſhall be ſtrongly beſeiged, and divers ſhall be impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and great and heavy Calamities ſhal happen. Shee is in this Scheme in <hi>Aquary,</hi> the houſe of <hi>Saturn,</hi> in conjunction with <hi>Venus,</hi> lady of the eighth houſe; both of them aſpected by the late full ſquare of <hi>Saturn,</hi> in the eight, the greateſt infortune, and in the worſt of houſes, <hi>but if wee
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:120066:15"/>beleive</hi> Mr. <hi>Lilly, be tells us, that the Moon is fortunate, becauſe conjoyned to Venus,</hi> but <hi>Venus</hi> her ſelfe here is Lady of th houſe of Death, and conſequently as bad as any <hi>Planet</hi> in the <hi>figure,</hi> except <hi>Saturn,</hi> who is locally in that houſe, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſowever, ſhe could never take off the malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in fluence of <hi>Saturn,</hi> who ſquares them both from the 8. for this is a rule which no Artiſt will deny: <hi>ſi times Saturnum, oppone Iovem, ſi Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem oppone Uenerem.</hi> The truth of the former rule, though he denyeth not, yet he cruelly tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Mr. <hi>Wharton</hi> for his application of it, to the <hi>Moon</hi> in that figure, but the event has anſwered his prediction, cont radicted Mr. <hi>Lillyes</hi> calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and this, and his other, almoſt infinite, and groſſe miſtakes this yeare, in point of Art, will chronicle him a <hi>dotard</hi> to all poſterity.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially this which followes which he ſtands ſo ſtiffly to maintain. <hi>Venus, ſaith he, is Lady of the Aſcendant, Mars Lord alſo thereof, is in the houſe of Inpiter, and Iupiter himſelfe, in the</hi> 10. <hi>the Moone alſo who hath uſually repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of the common condition of mankind, being not unfortunate, but applying to the conjunction of venus, gives us great reaſon, ſayth he, to hope well, and to live in aſſurance, that the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of England, ſhall not this yeare be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted with warre; That every man ſhall live at his own houſe. and in his owne Vocation, and Calling, quietly and ſecurely,</hi> Countreymen,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:120066:16"/>What ſay you to this? Certainly 'tis a faire pro miſe, but is it true? is he maſter of his word? no thing leſſe. We all know tis abſolutely falſe, yet everie man is not ſenſible, for all this of the greatneſſe and groſſeneſſe of this miſtake.</p>
            <p>It muſt not be underſtood barely, as an aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Mr. <hi>Lillyes,</hi> but as a confutation of Mr. <hi>Wharton,</hi> who predicted war, as he had good reaſon to doe, as <hi>God-willing. I</hi> ſhall ſhew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non, but that I may goe throughly, and ſoundly to work with him, I will firſt confute his miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken grounds.</p>
            <p>Verily ſaith he, this is no fiction of ours but the opinion of thoſe reverend profeſſors, who ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this ſcience, long before us: <hi>From whom O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riganus he ſayth drawes this inference, fol.</hi> 5.22. <hi>In anni et quartarum revolutionibus, ant the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matibus lunationum, ſi luna ſive firma ct potens, ſit in angulo velſuccedente dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, in dignittiabus ſuis ſive debilis, et cadens, extra dignitates, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicueri beneficeo alicui planetae,</hi> Jovi <hi>aut</hi> Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, <hi>ſignificat ſtatus populi fortunatins, quo lucrd eidem accreſcent, et abundnbunt neceſsaria; et ſi applicuerit</hi> Veneri, <hi>erit bilaritas, gaudiums, et frequentia connubiorum,</hi> which he thus tranſlates In the revolution of a yeare, and the ſeverall ſchemes of lunations, if the Moon, whether ſhe be ſtrong and powerfull, in an angle or a ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent houſe, in her own dignity, or admit ſhe be weak and cadent, yet if ſhe apply to any benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:120066:16"/>planet, as <hi>Iupiter</hi> or <hi>Venus,</hi> the ſtate or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the people, ſhall be ſignified ſucceſſefull and fortunate. in which yeare they ſhall encreaſe their eſtates, and abound in all manner of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie proviſions; and if that fortune to whom the Moone ſhall apply be <hi>Venus,</hi> (as now) the common people ſhall much rejoyce, be frolick, and very cheerfull. <hi>That theſe words are in Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus, I</hi> will not deny, nor that they be rightly rendered by him in Engliſh, but that he miſ-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands, and miſ-applyes <hi>Origamns,</hi> is plaine to a novice in this Art; for admit the moon to be ſo and ſo poſited, yea and ſo and ſo applying alſo [which is more then the rule requires,] and ſome other planet or planets in the ſcheme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting, ORIGANUS will not then affirme, that ſhe, ſo and ſo poſited, ſo and ſo applying, ſhall take off the ſignifications, of the other planets: for if this had bin his meaning, that the Moon ſhould rule all the Roſt, in that buſineſſe; the rules which Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> ſoone after tites out of <hi>Haly.</hi> had bin to no purpoſe: and his very quoting of <hi>Haly</hi> againſt Mr. <hi>Wharton,</hi> makes for me, againſt himſelfe. Againe <hi>Origanus</hi> ſpeaks, of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Venu's</hi> when they are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, they are not alwayes ſo, <hi>viz.</hi> when they are in the ſixth, eighth, tenth or twelfth, houſes. or are Lords of thoſe houſes: as here, <hi>Venus</hi> is Lady of the 8th. and the <hi>Moone</hi> her ſelfe, hath great dominion therein: and both <hi>Venus,</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:120066:17"/>the <hi>Moone</hi> are diſpoſed off by <hi>Saturne,</hi> who is locally in the 8th. in ſquare to them both: an ill aſpect, the worſt of houſes, and the greateſt in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. He does but trifle therefore, and abuſe <hi>Origanus,</hi> and che ancients, to affirme of them, which they never meant, nor did any man, that ever I ſaw, heard, or read of, ever underſtand him ſo he muſt therefore ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lk the authority of <hi>Orig.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Haly</hi> fits him to a haire, his authority ſhall carry it, if he puts his words, into true Engliſh <hi>He ſaith, Semper in revolutione, cave et reſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce Martem, quia ſi bonus fuerit, et in bono ſtatu, melius ſuccedit negotium, vaſſalorum regis, et exercituum. which he thus tranſlates into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh.</hi> In every revolution be well adviſed, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving judgement: and have reſpect to the place of <hi>Mars,</hi> for if he be well poſited, and in a good ſtate, the buſineſſe of the Kings Subjects, and their Armies, ſhall the better ſucceed. No Sir, this the buſineſſe of the Kings Subjects, and his Armies, ſhall the better ſucceed. He hath produced <hi>Haly,</hi> abſolutly againſt himſelfe: yet he ſaith, that this is an aſſured teſtimony, that the Common wealth of <hi>England,</hi> ſhall nor this year, be moleſted with Warr, or much troubled, and offended with the Souldier. <hi>Good Mr. Lilly, does exercitus in your Dictionary, ſignifie peace?</hi> if it ſignifies an Army, as mine ſaith it does, why then it is quite againſt you, not for you; he ſaith the <hi>King's</hi> Armies ſhall thrive, and you ſay we ſhall have peace.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:120066:17"/>Peace is the end of War indeed, but the Souldier is armed to fight. But he will be ſure, to make it for his parpole, one way or other: of it does ſpeak of War, it ſhall ſay, (or Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> will make it) that the Parliament ſhall beat the King; but <hi>Latine Haly Saith,</hi> that <hi>exercitus regis ſhall thrive:</hi> not the people, and their Armies. <hi>If the King's Armies thrive,</hi> the Parliaments muſt ſing <hi>Lacrymae:</hi> woe is me, well a day. But to be ſerious, <hi>Halyes meaning is,</hi> that when <hi>Mars</hi> is ſtrong, he does the leſſe miſchiefe: (the word is <hi>melius</hi> not <hi>bene</hi>) yet Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> and all men muſt grant, that <hi>Mars</hi> is <hi>ſemper in fortuna.</hi> Well <hi>Haly</hi> hath hitherto deceived him alſo: and yet he is reſolved, to try him once againe: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him, let him ſpeak, but know, that is you traduce him againe, his action of ſcandall againſt you, will be doubtleſſe, far more valid and vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. <hi>He quotes him, fol.</hi> 364. <hi>and tells us tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that be ſaith. Nota quod planeta, qui eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, et ſignificator anni, quando invenitur, in aliquo ſignorum, ſignificat, ſecundum proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ip fius planetae, et ſecundum ipſius proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem loci, in quo verſatur, de domibus figurae: et ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum ſtatum, et ejus fortunam, et infortunia: quia per fortunam, et bonuns ſtatum fignificat be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, et meliorem ſuceſſum et gaudium, et ſi Mars fuerit, ſignificat, quod homines vincent homines inimicos ſuos, &amp;c</hi> Which he tranſlates into Engliſh thus. Obſerve that planet, who is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficator
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:120066:18"/>of the year, &amp; in which of the 12. ſigns he is found; be aſſured, he ſhall ſignifie, according to theproperty of the Planer, Sign, &amp; houſe, of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, in which he is poſited, and according to his ſtate, for tune, or unfortunatneſſe, for that pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net well fortified, ſhall ſignifie good ſucceſſe, joy, gladneſſe, &amp;c. And if <hi>Mars</hi> ſhall at any time be ſo qualified, in a revolution, it imports the com. monaity ſhall overcome their Enemies. That <hi>Haly</hi> ſpeaks heere manifeſtly for Warr, he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſeth: for ſo his owne Engliſh renders him: but when he would inſinuate, that the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> or their army, ſhall overcome the <hi>King,</hi> (which if you obſerve he does) he ſhewes him. ſelfe a dotard, and no Scholler. It ſeemes he would if it were poſſible, make <hi>Haly,</hi> as guilty of treaſon, as himſelfe; but he ſaith, <hi>homines vincent homines:</hi> men ſhall overcome men: and J ſay, <hi>Haly</hi> was a loyall Subject, but <hi>Merlius Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> a Rebell.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> himſelfe confeſſeth, that <hi>Mars</hi> is the moſt conſicerable planer, not only in the <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallingreſſe,</hi> but alſo, in all other <hi>quarters and lunations of the yeare,</hi> and therefore he rightly judges, that ſome will object, (I my ſelfe am one of that number) that he might juſtly have beene ſuſpected, the forerunner of more Warte, and bloodſhed. Nor can the potency of <hi>Mars,</hi> in the <hi>vernall ingreſſe,</hi> hinder; for he is <hi>ſemper in fortuna.</hi> He is ſtrong <hi>I</hi> confeſſe in the vernall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:120066:18"/>ingreſſe, and at the time of the ſquare aſpect, of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Inpiter,</hi> but weak enough, all the year after. <hi>I</hi> hope Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> will not brag of his potency, at <hi>the Sans entring Cancer: at the con, junction of Saturne ond Mars: at the Eclipſe of the Moone, nor in many other not able aſpects, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening this yeare. I</hi> wonder therefore, that, Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> ſhould in ſuch plaine tearmes, aſſume (he uſeth to ſpeak Riddles commonly ſo darke, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>requires an <hi>Oedipus</hi> to unfold them) that it is be. yond his knowledge, if the devouring Sword, harme us this years: but eſpecially, that he ſhould be ſo confident, as to affirme, that it is poſitive in Aſtrology, that there will be this yeare, noe ſuch notorious diſtractions, to engage the King, dome in blood, or the City of <hi>London</hi> to a fury. We all know, <hi>Merlivus Anglicus, to be a lying Phophet its this,</hi> and that art was plaine for War, is manifeſt: not only from the reaſons before ſet downe, but alſo from the conjunction of <hi>Saturne and Mars in Gemini, the ſigne intercepted in the aſcendent, of the profectionall revolution, of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne and lupiter:</hi> Which makes Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> to cry out, <hi>ab hinc lacbrymae nostra Anglicanae, non a revolntione hu, us anni, vel ab has tam dira, et formidabili conjunctione, infortunarum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedunt:</hi> this indeed ſignifies Warre, buy by Mr. <hi>Lillies</hi> favour, the former reaſons, are far ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for Warre, then this: and if this had been the only cauſe of our ſufferings: there could not have
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:120066:19"/>been a blow ſtruck till the latter end of <hi>Iune,</hi> for this hapned not till then. I confeſſe this <hi>coniunct<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ion</hi> hapning in the ſigne intercepted in the <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent</hi> of the profectionall revolution, of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and an <hi>Eclipſe</hi> alſo, in that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſigne both of them in the 8th houſe, and neer <hi>Oculus Tauri,</hi> a moſt diſmall fixed Starre, will plague <hi>London,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lillyes</hi> beloved Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to purpoſe, and will bring ſo many, and ſo great calamities upon them, as would move even ſtones to pity, unleſſe <hi>God,</hi> the maker and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of all things, be overcome by their peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. to over rule the influence, of theſe heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bodyes.</p>
            <p>Theſe doubtleſſe were the reaſons, which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Mr. <hi>Wharton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Booker,</hi> this yeare, to predict Warr. I wonder infinitely at Mr <hi>Lillyes</hi> brazen impudence, in abuſing all ſuch as diſſent from his opinion, with ſuch ignominious epithits writing far truer then himſelfe: but much more that he ſhould bragg, that he hath found out a new manner of Aſtrology, heretofore either not knowne to the Antients, or elſe evillingly omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their writings, and would have us take it as a favour from him, for leaving us the <hi>Key of Aſtrology:</hi> poor ſimple animall, begot betweene a bitch wolfe, and an <hi>Incubus,</hi> neither by <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> nor <hi>Mercury.</hi> I am confident poſterity will never expreſſe any gratitude, for ſuch a key, as would lead them, if they follow it, into a maze,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:120066:19"/>and laberynth of endeleſſe errors. Me thinks that if this had ſlipt him, yet being premoniſht by Mr, <hi>Wharton,</hi> his old <hi>Antagoniſt,</hi> that this would be a year of martiall exployts in this Kingdom e it ſhould have made him pump hard, to have ſearcht the very entralls of Aſtrology, and if that would not have done it, then to have called to counſell, (as his manner is,) the <hi>Angell protector, or the guardian Angell of this Kingdome: for, flectere ſi nequeat ſuperos Acharonta movebit.</hi> What Mr <hi>Lilly,</hi> could not they informe you better? We uſe to ſay <hi>praemonitns, praemunitus,</hi> he that is forewarn'd is forearm'd; but it is not ſo with M. <hi>Lilly.</hi> he cannot plead ignorance, of what Mr. <hi>Wharton</hi> would have taught him, for 'tis certain that he ſaw his book, before his own was printed or elſe he could not, have called him foole there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, or have chriſtned him with ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious epithites.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mars</hi> I confeſſe as poſited in our Revolution, doth nor, during the vernall quarter, premon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate ſuch Warrs, ſlaughters, or ſuch grand com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, as our eyes have beheld, both before, and ſince, yet that he heer ſignifies ſlaughters, burnings, and miſchiefs, by fire, iron, pouder, and other things, ſubiect to the influence of <hi>Mars</hi> is plain and the event confirmes it, <hi>that Mars, as poſited in the vernall ingreſſe, threaten us with ſaddiſcontents, backſlidings in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous matters, great diſconſolation to the Clergy
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:120066:20"/>and high demands, or reſults, amongst the Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matic all (take notice he calls the Army Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks) he himſelfe confeſſeth</hi> as alſo that it ſig nifies a ſtrong endeavour, to ſettle the Juſt lawes of the Land, proceedings and cuſtomes of the people, and in regard that <hi>Mars</hi> was ſo potent, it ingaged moſt of the principall Gentry, and greateſt men in the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> to Deeds of <hi>Arms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Majeſties ſignificator in this Scheme, is very properly the Sun,</hi> poſited in the 5 t. houſe: for he is over the naturall ſignificator of <hi>Kings. (nam Sol pro Magiſtratu, luna pro ſubditis)</hi> and here he is the accidentall alſo; being Lord of the 10th.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Moone</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> are for the Patliament: <hi>Mars</hi> and the <hi>Moone</hi> are both ſtronger, then the <hi>Sun,</hi> in this Scheme: this quarter therefore, the King ſhall rather looſe, then get: <hi>Iupiter retro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grade,</hi> in the ſigne upon the 11th. houſe: ſignifies that the <hi>Kings friends,</hi> for a time, ſhall looſe themſelves, for want of Counſell, and mature ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercury</hi> is combuſt, the Kings friends ſhail therefore be betraid: and for a time grow wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and weaker: not ſtronger.</p>
            <p>And yet notwithſtanding this is an excellent Scheme, for his Majeſty, if it be rightly judged: for the <hi>part of fortune</hi> is with <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the very cuſpe of the 11th. And <hi>Mercury</hi> their diſpoſitor,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:120066:20"/>applying to the friendly <hi>trine of Iupiter:</hi> The Kings friends ſhall therefore at laſt be able to procure his re-eſtabliſhment, and that by deeds of Armes; for <hi>Mercury and the Sun too, are both in Aries, the houſe of Mars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iupiter</hi> is a ſlow ponderous planet, and beſides that retrograde in this figure: which will retard the buſineſſe, longer far then waa expected.</p>
            <p>If wee conſider the Parliaments ſignificators in this Scheme: They are the <hi>Moone, Venus, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and Mars: the Moone</hi> is ſtrong in the fourth houſe, in conjunction with <hi>Venus,</hi> Lady of the <hi>Aſcendent:</hi> this makes Mr. <hi>Lilly cry out oh happy Parliament, thon ſhalt ſtand for ever. and never be enforced, ſo much as to ſtoope.</hi> But who diſpoſes of the <hi>Moone</hi> and <hi>Venus?</hi> Does not <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne?</hi> What is he, <hi>almuten of the aſcendent,</hi> one of the Parliaments ſignificators, but the greateſt infortune, where is he? in the 8. houſe moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate, for it is the houſe of Death: who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of him? The <hi>Moone</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> where are they? in the 4th. houſe: what is the ſignification of that houſe? The end of all things.</p>
            <p>Why then by Mr. <hi>Lilles favour,</hi> this very Scheme, ſhall ſignifie: that notwithſtanding the Parliament, ſhall flouriſh yet a while, yet in the end, they ſhall be conquered, and brought low, yea many of them ſhall dye a death, ſhamefull, and ignominious: nor can the double mutuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:120066:21"/>of <hi>Saturne and Venus by houſe, of Saturn and the Moone by triplicity</hi> hinder: for <hi>Satuone almuten of the Parliaments aſcendent,</hi> Their houſe of life, is in the houſe of death, extreamely, unfortunate, and beholds their other ſignificators viz. both the <hi>Moone</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> with a hatefull ſquare, in the fourth houſe, the end of all things, What think you Mr. <hi>Lilly?</hi> does not this ſignifie unto them death? or at leaft diſhonour?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If we conſider, the ſquare of Saturne and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter, the 29 of March ſoon following the ſuns ingreſſe into Aries, about 26 of Leo is in the cuſpe of the Aſcendent, and Iupiter retrograde very neer the cuſp; who yet comes to be direct, before he comes to the degree of the aſcendent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jupiter therefore &amp; the Sun are in this ſcheme the <hi>Parliaments</hi> ſignificators but principally <hi>Iupiter, for plus valet plenota, corporali praeſentia quam dominio abſentriae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jupiter is a very good planet (Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi>) and to ſpeake truth he is the beſt, and moſt benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent of the ſeaven: but is he not retrogade Mr <hi>Lilly?</hi> that ſignifies, that though <hi>Iupiter,</hi> wil ſupport the parliament for a time, yet they ſhall grow weaker and weaker, run backwards, looſe, but not ſuddainly, in regard the <hi>Sun,</hi> is ſo ſtrong in the very degree of his exaltation: and from thence beholding <hi>the Aſcendent and Iupiter with a freindly</hi> trine. But Good <hi>Mr Lilly,</hi> let me aske you one queſtion more, what houſes are
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:120066:21"/>
               <hi>Iubiter</hi> Lord of the 8. and the fourth? Death therefore and diſhonour, ſhall be their guerdon at laſt, for as <hi>Iupiter</hi> is <hi>Lord</hi> of the fourth, he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the end, and as he is Lord of the 8. he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies death, eſpecially being in the <hi>aſcendent,</hi> the houſe of life, as he is retrograde and 2 <hi>ſlow. Planet,</hi> ſo he ſignifies that they ſhall go by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees. <hi>Leo is a regall ſigne the ſun alſo is in a nother, this intimates their ambition,</hi> That they would be <hi>Kings, but Iupitor retrograde in le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one,</hi> ſpoyles their Maieſty, dethrones them quite eſpecially if you conſider, that <hi>Saturn in the</hi> 10. ſends his ſquare to <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the <hi>Aſcendent.</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leieve it Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> they muſt fall, and have a rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing knock. His maieſties Signiſicators in this Scheme are <hi>Saturn, the Moon, and Mercury, Saturn</hi> is by nature an inforrune. yea the greateſt of all, out what houſes is he Lord of? the 8.9. and 10. from the 10 pray God there were not, nor yet be ſome treachery to take away his Maieſties life. <hi>I</hi> am much aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid that <hi>lurida terribiles miſcent aconita noverca.</hi> But in regard that <hi>Venus</hi> his diſpoſitrix is ſo ſtrong, <hi>I</hi> hope providence wil preſerve him and will help him to evade their malice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturn</hi> as he is <hi>Lord</hi> of the 10 from the 10th. will reſtore him, though with much diſſiculty for <hi>Saturn</hi> retards all chings, and gives what ſoever he gives, with labour &amp; difficulty. <hi>Saturn</hi> in the 10. in ſquare to the aſcendent, and to <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:120066:22"/>retrograde therein, ſignifyes that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentſhall be forced, though unwillingly, to reſtore unto the King, his Rights and dignityes, which <hi>Mercury</hi> lord of the ſecond, in the cuſpe of the tenth plainly alſo denotes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercury</hi> is Lord of the Parliaments houſe of ſubſtance, and of the Kings too: now not farre from the cuſpe of the 10th. therefore his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties eſtate is not farre from regaining.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Dragous tayle</hi> in the culpe of the 11th. ſignifies many falſe friends to his Majeſty, who will not long from this time appeare, pretending faire meaning hollowly; doubtleſſe they will buy him, and fell him, once againe, and ſlander him what they can it impedites alſo the actions of his trueſt friends, for his ſuccour, but <hi>dabit Deus his quoque finem.</hi> The Prince will bring them on their knees, for <hi>Saturne</hi> is Lord of the 5 t. and the caſe will be much altered anon <hi>I</hi> doubt not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In May laſt,</hi> there hapned a conjunction of the <hi>Royall Sun</hi> and <hi>Sullen Saturne,</hi> in the 10 houſe: which did much impedite his <hi>Majeſtyes Actions,</hi> a long time: and put his very life in danger<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: but <hi>caput Draconis</hi> being there it could not hurt his life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercury is both for the King.</hi> and parliament but he diſpoſeth of the <hi>Sun.</hi> and <hi>Saturne,</hi> and is conjoyned to <hi>Mars,</hi> the King could not there.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:120066:22"/>fore, as long as the fury of this conjunction laſted, thrive in Military affaires, nor the City of <hi>London</hi> riſe to help him: it will do ſomething one day: <hi>Oh London</hi> take heed, many remarkable Aſpects have and ſhall happen this yeare in <hi>Gemini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Summer begins the</hi> 10th. <hi>of Iune,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Here ſhould been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted 2. Schemes one for the Sun's ingreſſe into <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of <hi>Saturn</hi> &amp; <hi>Iupiter.</hi> The firſt ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ning IYNE the 10. the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the 10 of IVNE</note> 10. <hi>minuts paſt</hi> 11. <hi>a Clock at night:</hi> at which time, the <hi>glorious Sun, enters Cancer:</hi> The <hi>Moone,</hi> within 3. quarters of an houre, being in conjunction with him: obſcuring his bright body, and cauſing a great and fearfull <hi>Eclipſe:</hi> but not viſible to us: all the planets being at that time, ſubterranean, in this <hi>Iupiter</hi> and the <hi>Moon</hi> are for the <hi>Parliament Iupiter and the Sun for the King:</hi> for <hi>Iupiter</hi> is Lord of the firſt, and tenth.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Moon</hi> is combuſt in the fourth Houſe, which very thing would have abſolutely deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Parliament, at that time, or neere it; had not the <hi>Dragons head,</hi> bin ſo neere the <hi>Moone,</hi> and the <hi>Sun</hi> been Eclipſed; this therefore up holds for a while their drooping ſpirits, long it cannot. The <hi>Eclipſe of the Sun,</hi> hurts not the <hi>King</hi> much, in regard it is not viſiale, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the effects of this <hi>Eclipſe,</hi> will be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, to us: yet ſome miſchiefe it doubtleſſe did. The <hi>Dragons tayle</hi> in the roth. gives feare of poyſon, or of hurt by a Horſe, or by riding, or elſe ſome miſcheiſe, by fire or Iron. God bleſſe his <hi>Majeſty</hi> from danger of death, and from
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:120066:23"/>ſcandalls, and ſlanders, raiſed againſt him, by black mouth d Villaines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iupiter</hi> the other ſignificator both of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> is in the 7th. houſe, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the aſcendent, the Parl. therefore will oppoſe the Parliament: and great diſſenſion will doubt. leſſe be amongſt themſelves, enough to have cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their utter undoing, had not <hi>Mercury</hi> the diſpoſitor of <hi>Iupiter,</hi> beheld the <hi>aſcendent,</hi> by a <hi>trine eſpect,</hi> this will make them peece againe for a time, but <hi>Saturne and Mars</hi> in their ſecond houſe, will ſignifie great expence of Treaſure, and much loſſe by fire, and War, at leaſt to ſome of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iupiter</hi> as he is Lord of the 10th. is in the 10th. from the 10th. and beholds it, with a ſextile aſpect, and <hi>Saturne</hi> Lord of the 11th. in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, with a trine. This will doubtleſſe ſignifie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, to his <hi>Maieſty</hi> and the recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, yea and his priſtine honour.</p>
            <p>Not long after the <hi>Suns enterance into Cancer</hi> viz. about the 28 of <hi>Iune,</hi> there hapened <hi>a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of</hi> Saturne <hi>and</hi> Mars the two malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and worſt of planets, <hi>in Gemini, neere ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Tauri, in the</hi> 8th. <hi>houſe of Heaven: whoſe</hi> inſluence will produce, wonderfull alterations, but not without other concurrent cauſes, as Mr. <hi>Lilly well obſerveth,</hi> but there are other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current cauſes enough [<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> too many, if it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:120066:23"/>
               <hi>God</hi>] to cooperate, with this conjunction, both before &amp; ſubſequent, <hi>eſpecially the eclipſe of the moon within three degrees of the very Place of the conjunction it ſelfe: and</hi> it hapens alſo in the 7 and 8. houſes of heaven, very neer unto <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culas tauri,</hi> and the very body of <hi>Saturne,</hi> and this Mr. <hi>Lilly himſelfe, coufeſſeth, ſaying that this conjunction is neer oculus tauri, a moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent fixed ſtar, if we beleeve either our own ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience or that of the ancients, for there did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver happen any Eclipſe conjunction, or oppoſition of the Superiours neer that Part of Gemini, but it produced admirable and wonderfull effects:</hi> add to this that the firſt conjunction, of <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the fiery trigon, was in the yeare 603. in oppoſition, almoſt to the very degree of this coniunction. We have ſad cauſe [I am ſure, his Maieſty hath] to remember the effects of the Eclipſe of the Sun in the tenth of <hi>Gemini anno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 1639. much more reaſon will the Parliament have to remember this coniunction, and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the Moon in that place.</p>
            <p>Yea Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> himſelfe confeſſeth, this a very ſad pofition of heaven for the Parliament, able utterly upon the firſt fight (yea and the ſecond too) to puzzle a weak, (yea Mr. <hi>Lillyes strong</hi>) affection: for <hi>I</hi> doubt, he himſelf hath no more then humane principles; <hi>We have</hi> Mars <hi>ſaith he,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:120066:24"/>their Significator</hi> (becauſe <hi>Lord of the Aſcendent in the</hi> 8th houſe, <hi>in conjunction with</hi> Saturn. <hi>neer</hi> Oculus Tauri, <hi>a ſad Planet, and more diſmall fixed star: The houſe he alſo confeſſeth, to be the worſt of houſes, and that it ſignifies to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, a ſad and diſtracted condition, yea he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſeth further, that it imports a parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſtrugling and gaſping for breath, and life and that</hi> London <hi>alſo is the moſt of any city in</hi> Europe <hi>concerned in this conjunction: as alſo that the leaſt miſehief, that thereupon can happen to that City, Will be ſedition, uproares, famine, if not Gloudſhed. And a little before, hee is yet more ingenious, confeſsing poſitively, thas (God out of his infinite mercy not preventing) war, and bloudſhed will ſucceed in this very City Page 39. and I fear they will find all this, and much more true enough, which I ſhall anou diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mutantur regna, et dominia, et fides, ſectaeque et opiniones hominum, dum mutantur auges pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netaru, de figno in ſignum, dico illarum genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, quarum fignificator erit plaeneta, augi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mntae: mutatioque; erit ad bonum, vel ad malum, ſecundum naturam ſignificatorum ſuperiorum conjunctionum illorum temporum, et ſecundum naturam ſigni permutationis.</hi> That is King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and Governments, Leagues, Sects, and mens opinions, do change, and vary, when the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:120066:24"/>anges of the planets move out of one figne into another: I ſay of theſe nations, whoſe ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator, is the planet of the changed auges: And this alteration ſhall be for good or ill, according to the nature of the ſigniſicators of the ſuperior conjunctions of thoſe times, and according to the nature of the ſigne of mutation. <hi>Mars</hi> is the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſignificator of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe <hi>absſis</hi> or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phelium,</hi> is at preſent in four ſigns, twenty nine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, fifty two minutes, and one and twenty ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds. that is 29. deg. 52. min. 21. of <hi>Leo:</hi> and sin the year 1656. this <hi>abſis</hi> will remove into Virgo about which year <hi>M Lylly</hi> ſaith we muſt expect a ſtrange <hi>Catastrophe</hi> in this Common wealth, and <hi>Monarchy</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for <hi>Mars</hi> cannot protect Aries and Uirgo, whom he beholds not: all this is Mr. <hi>Lyllyes, I</hi> will not own it, nay <hi>I</hi> ſhall willingly and ingeniouſly confeſſe, that I underſtand not, why this ſhould be ſo fatall to <hi>England, or to London,</hi> as he would make us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive: yet am I clear of his opinion, in that which followes, that a very ſad diſaſtre to the City is much to be feared, long before that time, Have a care <hi>London,</hi> thou art already ſtrongely and ſtrangely threatned, and wilt be ſuddainly more, have a care thou rebelleſt no longer againſt thy King, thou maiſt put an end to theſe Wars when thou pleaſeſt, and thou hadſt a principall ſtroake in beginning them: do what thou meanſt to do,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:120066:25"/>quickly, 'twill be elſe too late: Remember the old prophecy, part of which thou knoweſt to be already fulfilled. <hi>Lincoln</hi> was <hi>London</hi> is, and <hi>Yorke</hi> Chall be, the greateſt City of the three.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scorpio</hi> a fixed <hi>ſigne aſcends,</hi> and I ſhall eaſily grant Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> that all the angles of the figure, are alſo fixed and in trine to Piſces, the ſigne aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending at the <hi>Parliaments</hi> firſt fitting, but that all or any of theſe, ſhall or can <hi>(rebus ſic ſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us)</hi> ſignifie that the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhall ſtand firm and not be diſſipated I abſolutely deny and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the contrary to be true, and evident in point of Art. And let him but produce good Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors to ſecond his aſſertion, and I will willingly yeeld him the Bucklers in this caſe, I thinke any Artiſt will think him mad or worſe to judg this a ſufficient reaſon therefore the Lord of the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent being with <hi>Saturn,</hi> and <hi>Oculus Tauri,</hi> he knowes [or at leaſt ſhould know] <hi>ſignum ut corpus Planetaut anima,</hi> there is little promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by any ſigne of <hi>Heaven.</hi> which hath no pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net in it, nor yet well aſpecting it, he is almoſt aſhamed <hi>I</hi> perceive of this reaſon by that which followes. <hi>for he confeſſeth that their unfaithfull branches, and rotten boughs, muſt be lopt off, We</hi> deſire no more, there are for all this (I hope) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe honeſt men amongſt them, who greive at the <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms ſufferings,</hi> and would help it if they could.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:120066:25"/>
            <p>When Mr. <hi>Lilly affirmeth,</hi> that this conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſignifieth good to the <hi>Parliament; quia ex duabus infortunis fit fortuna;</hi> he himſelf contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts what he ſaid before, and dotes moſt wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly, moſt miſerably. I deny not the <hi>Aphoriſme ('tis Ptolemies)</hi> but I deny this ſence of it; ('tis Mr. <hi>Lillies</hi>) I doubt not indeed but it will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce much good, to the <hi>Kingdome;</hi> none to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> or the City of <hi>London.</hi> Nor can the <hi>North node of Venus</hi> or <hi>caput draconis,</hi> ſave and defend them, (as he would have it) their ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator is too far diſtant from <hi>caput draconis;</hi> and too much afflicted, to be holpen by him. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he cries not out ſtill, <hi>why cannot the Citizens thrive and be pleaſant? a time is now approaching, which imports felicity unto them: this he ſaid in Julyes obſervations,</hi> but they will curſe him for lying before the end of <hi>Febr.</hi> next.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturne</hi> in the figure of the Suns ingreſſe into the vernall point <hi>Aries,</hi> in the eighth houſe, ſignifies a dearth of ſuch creatures, as the ſigne repreſents wherein he is; the ſigne he is in at that time is <hi>Taurus;</hi> which ſignifies great cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, oxen, horſes, cowes; but this Conjunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> in the eighth houſe, is in <hi>Gemini,</hi> which will not onely cauſe many great, and grieveous ſickneſſes, yea very deadly ones, but many violent, and untimely deaths this year, by the ſword, even in cold blood: <hi>Lucas</hi> and <hi>Liſle</hi> are not forgotten yet: this ſignifies the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:120066:26"/>plague alſo, or ſome peſtilentiall diſeaſe, in the City of <hi>London;</hi> great diſcontent, great ſcarcity of graine, and corne, though it will not be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as yet.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> in this ſcheme, are the Kings friends; <hi>Jupiter</hi> is accidentally ſtrong, Lord of the fifth, uponwhoſe cuſpe a watery ſigne is placed, the <hi>Prince</hi> therefore &amp; the King's friends ſhall prevaile at Sea. Soone after this conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on happened, the <hi>Prince</hi> appear'd with the Fleet, upon the Sea, and put forth a Declaration, that He was reſolved to adventure His deareſt life, to re-eſtabliſh our Soveraigne, His Royall Father: which He will undoubtedly do; for <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter</hi> lowres upon <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> with a hatefull <hi>Square.</hi> Never let Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> ſay he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do it, in regard that <hi>Jupiter</hi> is not eſſentially dignified; but rather let him anſwer me this queſtion: is not <hi>Jupiter</hi> much ſtronger, yea far more fortunate then <hi>Mars?</hi> is he not alſo poſited in a better houſe? The <hi>Square</hi> betweene <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and the infortunes, will produce almoſt infinite diſputes, about our Laws, Cuſtomes, and Priviledges, Religion, Covenants, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Saturne</hi> better dignified then <hi>Mars,</hi> ſignifies ſcarcity of Proviſion for man. <hi>Mars</hi> more ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vated, ſhewes that the ſword will prevaile. Whoſe ſword Mr. <hi>Lilly?</hi> pray ſpeake the truth, in plaine Engliſh: why he confeſſeth, that it ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues the Souldier muſt doe ſtrange things, or
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:120066:26"/>elſe we periſh faith he; he meanes himſelfe and the Army. Alas, alas, this is ill newes indeed, who can help it? God ſend us never worſe. Oh, but Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> even in his very Agony, hath one trick left; ('tis Treaſon I fear) let us hear it; he exhorts the whole Kingdome, yea moſt earneſtly, to take the Parliaments part: Why ſo? what againſt their Soveraigne, thou Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor? What then ſhall become of <hi>Jeſus</hi> ſaid <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late?</hi> what ſhall become of our Soveraigne then ſay I? the <hi>Jewes</hi> ſaid, <hi>Crucifie him, crucifie him;</hi> and <hi>Lilly</hi> ſaith the like in effect, as you ſhall hear anon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Venus</hi> applies to a ſextile of <hi>Jupiter;</hi> he in <hi>Virgo,</hi> ſhe in <hi>Cancer,</hi> at the time of the aſpect: His Majeſty therefore may expect aſſiſtance, from His friends in <hi>France,</hi> becauſe <hi>Jupiter</hi> is in <hi>Virgo,</hi> the aſcendent of <hi>Paris:</hi> much from <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> becauſe <hi>Venus</hi> is in <hi>Cancer;</hi> the royall Sun being at that time in <hi>Cancer,</hi> ſignifies that the <hi>Scots</hi> ſhall not regard their own profit ſo much, to neglect the reſtitution of His Majeſty as M. <hi>Lilly</hi> would ſuggeſt, but without any grounds at all in art, for he gives this to be his reaſon, for this his prediction; <hi>the Moon,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds</hi> Cancer, <hi>and not the Sun at all, by any aſpect:</hi> which is abſolutely falſe, for the Moon beholds not <hi>Cancer</hi> at all, either in the radix of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction, or at the time of the aſpect, betweene <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Venus;</hi> for in the radix ſhe is in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quary</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:120066:27"/>at the time of the aſpect in <hi>Gemini;</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of which ſignes, behold <hi>Cancer</hi> at all: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Sun</hi> is both in the radix, and alſo at the time of the aſpect, in <hi>Cancer.</hi> which is far ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; and much better, then any aſpect to the <hi>Sun</hi> in this regard.</p>
            <p>But that any or all of the Kings friends, ſhall ever be able to re-eſtabliſh His Majeſty, is nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive in Aſtrology (if we beleeve Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> when he lieth) why ſo I pray Sir? ſurely becauſe it is ſo often, doubly, trebly, yea doubly and trebly affirmed. And I call heaven and earth to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I for my part, cannot ſee, (nor can I hear of from him) any ſufficient reaſon in Art, to the contrary; I know there are many for it, and very ſtrong ones too: Two negatives make an affirmative, but two hundered affirmatives, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make a negative. The beſt and moſt valid reaſon, that Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> gives againſt it, is this; that when King <hi>James</hi> came to the Crowne, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> were in Conjunction, in the eighth degree of <hi>Sagitarius,</hi> and this Conjunction is, faith he, almoſt in the very ſame degree, of the oppoſite ſigne: whereby he would faine inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, that this Conjunction imports deſtruction to His Majeſty, and His family, but why ſo M. <hi>Lilly?</hi> neither <hi>Saturne</hi> nor <hi>Mars</hi> are His Majeſties ſignificators, and therefore have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with Him, or with His family; but <hi>Mars</hi> is Lord of the aſcendent, and therefore
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:120066:27"/>imports deſtruction to the Parliament unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dably, unleſſe they in time compoſe the buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>Another of M. <hi>Lillies</hi> reaſons, but more wide then the former, is this: <hi>Piſces,</hi> ſaith he, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, when the Parliament began, and the twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth degree of <hi>Sagitary</hi> culminated, and <hi>Mars</hi> ſaith he was in 10. degree of <hi>Sagitary,</hi> in <hi>Square</hi> dexter, to the place of this Conjunction; this ſtill ſignifies deſtruction to them, not to him: for <hi>Mars</hi> has his triplicity in <hi>Piſces,</hi> &amp; therefore ſignifies the Parliament, now he coming to the Conjunction of <hi>Saturne,</hi> in the eighth houſe, neere <hi>oculus tauri,</hi> and in the ſame place, which he afflicted, with his owne <hi>Square,</hi> at their firſt ſitting: this muſt needs ſignifie, at leaſt their diſſolution, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, and diſhonour; if not the block and gib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet, for ſome of them.</p>
            <p>To this give me leave to adde, the predicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the dying Independent Prieſt, (I meane M. <hi>Saltmarſh</hi>) who is confidently reported, to have had the apparition of, and diſcourſe with an Angel; who if ſent from God, (as its verily beleeved) is an invincible argument, to warrant his prediction good. It ſeemes he told <hi>Fairfax</hi> to his face, that God had ſent him to him, to let him underſtand, that he perſecuted his Saints, had done many things amiſſe, and therefore that he and his Army both, ſhould come to utter ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iue, and that with ſpeed. <hi>Saltmarſh</hi> was well, when he delivered this meſſage, and gave <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:120066:28"/>a ſigne, for the truth of his prediction, that ſuch a day and houre, he the meſſenger him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould die, and ſo he did at the time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed. Moſt men in the Kingdome have heard of this, yea and many do verily beleeve it to be true; but very few ponder it as they ought: for my part, it ſticks with me; and Ile aſſure M. <hi>Lilly,</hi> that I verily expect the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sun</hi> in this ſcheme is the Kings ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſaith M. <hi>Lilly,</hi> who is locally in the ninth, which is the twelfth from the tenth, <hi>Ergo</hi> ſaith he, the King is Captived. True, He is ſo; but woe be to them that did it: pray <hi>Sir</hi> what thinke you of thoſe, that ſide with them, who have laid violent hands upon the Lords Anointed? Ile an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for you, for this once, he is a Rebell, and the worſt of Traytors.</p>
            <p>The motions of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars.</hi> are ſwift indeed, as M. <hi>Lilly</hi> obſerveth rightly. for they greatly exceed their meane motions; yet am I not of his opinion; that the actions, ſignified by the Conjunction of theſe two Planets, ſhall be carried on, and proſecuted, with ſo great ſpeed, as he affirmeth, with great fury and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence they will; for <hi>Saturne</hi> is the floweſt of all the Planets, he is 30 years going about the <hi>Zodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ack;</hi> &amp; therefore his effects, wil not quicklyceaſe; and yet much the ſooner for his quick motion.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe the Conjunction of theſe two
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:120066:28"/>malevolent Planets, with <hi>oculus tauri,</hi> in the eighth houſe, and in <hi>Gemini,</hi> where <hi>Mars</hi> made his ſquare, at the Parliaments firſt ſitting; will ſignifie ſingular actions, and of very high con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernement, eſpecially to <hi>London,</hi> and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Anno</hi> 1635. and 1636. <hi>Saturne</hi> tranſiting <hi>Sagitarius, London</hi> ſmarted with the Plague, how much more will he and <hi>Mars,</hi> afflict her now, they being conjoyn'd in <hi>Gemini,</hi> in the eight houſe, neere the <hi>Buls eye?</hi> O <hi>London,</hi> let me tell thee plainly, and ſeriouſly, and truly, that (if thou makeſt not an early peace, I meane a ſuddaine attonement, with thy angry God, and thy abuſed Soveraigne, his Anointed, and Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent here; againſt whom thou wert with the firſt, (nay the very firſt) that Rebell'd, and led'ſt divers Countries, by thy example, to drinke deepe of the poyſonous cup of Rebellion, Schiſme, Hereſie, &amp;c.) thou ſhalt ſoon match <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in accurſedneſſe; thou ſhalt ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but frowning wrath in the clouds: but Lightning and Thunder, in the mouth of the foure winds: the heavens ſhall be an artillery houſe of haile-ſtones; No Planet ſhall revolve any thing, but vaſtation: Earthquakes ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve thy joynts: and all thy glorious buildings, ſhall but cruſh their owners, with their fals, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording them unasked tombes, and ſepulchres: The damps of the earth, ſhall breed nothing but
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:120066:29"/>plagues; the clouds ſhall drop downe leanneſſe, on thy fields: the Sword, Famine, and Peſtilence, (thoſe dreadfull meſſengers of Gods vengeance) ſhall fall upon thee, till thou art quite conſumed. Oh <hi>London, London,</hi> remember, remember, the man, who for a time, went night and day, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about thy ſtreets, Woe, Woe, Woe. I ſpeake a thing well knowne to thouſands, yet inhabiting within thy Wals; who then ſaw him, and heard him too; yet neither they, nor any man elſe, that ever I could hear of yet, could (though ſome of them much deſired it) ever learne, what, who, or whence he was. Beleeve it, the day of thy viſitation is almoſt come, and will ſhortly preſent it ſelfe, to thy amazed eyes, in a dreadfull, crimſon hiew; unleſſe with <hi>Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh</hi> thy ſiſter City, thou doeſt ſuddainly waſh away thoſe crimſon ſpots of innocent blood, which thou haſt ſpilt, with thy penitent teares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here</hi> two ſchemes or figures of heaven ſhould have been pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,the firſt of the Suns entrance into <hi>Libra,</hi> the other of the Eclipſe of the Moone, the firſt hapneth the 12. of <hi>September,</hi> the Eclipſe the 29. of <hi>November.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hercle reſtat regnum aliud piis, Coelo ſub amplo, beſtia cum cadot Dandum, potoſtatiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſumoe Jus, pede ſub dominante Chriſti Stratis Tyrannum verticibus.</p>
            <p>Theſe Verſes M. <hi>Lilly</hi> placed under the ſcheme of the Suns ingreſſe into <hi>Aries,</hi> but I have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fferred them hither, and much more properly,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:120066:29"/>they are left by him un-Engliſhed, I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paraphraſe them thus:</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="poem">
                        <l>When <hi>Charls</hi> ſhall Reigne againe (as ſure he ſhall</l>
                        <l>And th' <hi>Weſtminſterian Hydra</hi> reele and fall,</l>
                        <l>(That beaſt compos'd of all religions, Sects,</l>
                        <l>Schiſmes, Hereſies, which long this land have vext</l>
                        <l>Loſt happineſſe will doubtleſſe then appear</l>
                        <l>To righteous men, the beaſt then falling, where</l>
                        <l>Such tyranny and oppreſſion ſhall give way</l>
                        <l>To Chriſt's Vicegerent <hi>Charls</hi> his nobler ſway.</l>
                        <l>And milder regiment: Oh may, oh may</l>
                        <l>That joyfull day with ſpeed it ſelfe preſent</l>
                        <l>To crowne our hopes, even drown'd in diſcontent,</l>
                        <l>The daies at hand: harke, harke, methinkes I hear,</l>
                        <l>The bugle horne of watchfull <hi>Chanticleere</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To uſher't in, and ſummon all thoſe brave</l>
                        <l>Heroick Loyall ſoules, who ſhall and have</l>
                        <l>Been true t' their King, and Soveraigne, with joy</l>
                        <l>To welcome re-eſtabliſht <hi>Charls:</hi> thoſe quoy</l>
                        <l>Diſloyall Traytors, who thus long have kept</l>
                        <l>Thrir Soveraigne their ſlave, and ſo have heap't</l>
                        <l>Vengeance on their owne heads, to houle, lament,</l>
                        <l>And curſe the day they were a Parliament:</l>
                        <l>Harke how the very ghoſts of thoſe who dy'd</l>
                        <l>Rebels to <hi>Charls,</hi> and him ſo oft bely'd;</l>
                        <l>Harke how they skrike, they howle, they weepe, they groane,</l>
                        <l>Harke how they now lament, bewaile and moane!</l>
                        <l>Harke how they <hi>Lilly</hi> junior <hi>Merlin</hi> curſe</l>
                        <l>For's lying Oracles; the very nurſe</l>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:120066:30"/>
                        <l>Of their Rebellion! harke how they lowre</l>
                        <l>And even expreſſe their horrour to this houre!</l>
                        <l>But harke how th' nobler ghoſts of thoſe who dy'd</l>
                        <l>By deeds of armes on King and Countries ſide,</l>
                        <l>Rejoyce with lyricke ſongs, harke how they ſing</l>
                        <l>And ſinging weepe, becauſe their Royall King,</l>
                        <l>Being re-inthron'd, his happy Government</l>
                        <l>Enjoy they cunnot now, muſt reſt content,</l>
                        <l>Joyfull at's re-eſtabliſhment indeed</l>
                        <l>But very penſive that through want of heed.</l>
                        <l>And their ill fates, the date of their ſhort lives</l>
                        <l>So ſoon expir'd: and this ſinging drives</l>
                        <l>Them eke to weeepe, who would not wiſh to be</l>
                        <l>Againe but for his future ſervice, ſee</l>
                        <l>Their piety, and ſeeing wonder,</l>
                        <l>Raſh fate ſo ſoone ſhould cut their threads aſunder.</l>
                        <l>Harke how a quire of Angels in a ring,</l>
                        <l>Doe round about them bleſſed muſick ſing.</l>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Harveſt begins the 12 of <hi>September,</hi> 28 min: paſt two a clock, in the afternoone: at which time <hi>Capricorne</hi> aſcends. <hi>Capricorne</hi> is the houſe of <hi>Saturne,</hi> whom I find in the fixth houſe, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd by the <hi>Moone</hi> in the twelfth; both being the Parliaments ſignificators; looke to it Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this is a nipping ſcheame, &amp; will aſſuredly ſqueeze thoſe ſpunges, which have ſuckt up His Majeſties, and the Kingdomes rights, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, eſpecially fith the <hi>Moone</hi> is with the Dragons taile in <hi>Sagitarius;</hi> the oppoſite ſigne
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:120066:30"/>to <hi>Gemini.</hi> Looke to thy ſelfe <hi>London, Saturne</hi> is in <hi>Gemini,</hi> in the ſixth houſe, in perfect oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the <hi>Moone:</hi> the Kings ſignificators, are now indifferent well poſited, infinitely ſtronger then his adverſaries, and in better houſes, me thinkes this ſhould make M. <hi>Lilly,</hi> to ſhrug his ſhoulders; and the Parliament to gaſpe, both for breath, and life. I confeſſe this is but a ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe yet, though very grieveous, and not cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by any other Phyſick, then by the Perſonall Treaty; which they will ſcarce take long enough to doe them good; if they will not, I muſt tell them, that their criticall day, of their great cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mactericall year approacheth, and is hard at hand: I meane the Eclipſe of the <hi>Moone,</hi> the 20 of <hi>November,</hi> and that will doubtleſſe make impatient death preſſe out their few remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirits.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Sun,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the <hi>Moon.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Moone,</hi> and <hi>Mars,</hi> are for the Parlirment: <hi>mercury</hi> is the Kings ſignificator, the <hi>Moon</hi> is Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>Gemini,</hi> in the ſeventh and eighth hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of heaven; death therefore, ignominy, and reproach, are all falling upon the heads of ſome great ones, at <hi>Weſtmiuſter.</hi> Farewell Command at Sea; the Ships muſt be ſome ſanke, ſome ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſome will revolt, none will remaine: the <hi>Sun</hi> is in their aſcendent with the <hi>Dragons taile;</hi> beware a horſes night-cap; ſcape it if you can, 'tis ill phyſick, what thinke you Mr. <hi>Lilly?</hi> will not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:120066:31"/>this crop away the ſuperfluous branches, you talke of? It will make the people revolt. You remember that the Ecliſe of the <hi>Sun</hi> in 1639. was a very great cauſe of the Kings ſorrow; how much greater ſorrow will this cauſe to thoſe, who have thus long ſed him, with the bred of bitterneſſe, and water of affliction? for if you marke it, it happens in the ſame ſigne, houſe, and almoſt degree of the ſigne, that the Conjunction of <hi>Saturne</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> did: and cooperates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. This indeed will worke ſuddainly, will divide betweene the very bones, and marrow. His Majeſties ſignificator <hi>Mercury,</hi> is ſingularly poſited in the ſecond houſe in Conjunction with <hi>Venus,</hi> who is in reception by houſe with <hi>Jupiter.</hi> What thinke you <hi>Sir,</hi> will this reſtore His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty or not? Take heed, if it does, as aſſuredly it will, you know who has <hi>Gemini</hi> aſcending at his nativity, a halter ſtretch him. Let me tell you <hi>Sir,</hi> this wil reſtore His Majeſty, (unleſſe He be made away by poyſon) and I hope betweene this and <hi>Febr:</hi> next; I beſeech God protect Him, and my hopes are ſtrong he will.</p>
            <p>This Eclipſe alſo ſignifies death, at leaſt great danger of death, to a Lady of very great fame and worth.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Booker</hi> ſaith well, that it is much to be doubted, whether the aire will be cleare enough, to have the Eclipſe viſible; becauſe of the near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Eclipſed luminary, to the body of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:120066:31"/>
               <hi>Saturne,</hi> and the oppoſition of the <hi>Sun,</hi> cauſing a very great <hi>apertio portarum;</hi> to raine, winds, and a great diſtemper in the aire, much about that time; but certaine I am, it will be felt, and ſo ſmartly, that diverſe will curſe the very day of their births, and the wombe that brought them forth. Looke to't Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> you and all your friends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eclipſis Lunae in primis decem gradibus Gemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum, ſacerdotibus, &amp; in quovis ordine ſacris ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatis; diſſentionem, lites, &amp; ſeditiones aggerit; odia infanda, legum cotemptum, &amp; pietatis etiam neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectum concitat; &amp; in curſiones, &amp; rapinas hosti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um minatur.</hi> The <hi>Moone</hi> Eclipſed in the firſt ten degrees of <hi>Gemini,</hi> ſtirs up amongſt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Clergy, diſſentions, ſtrifes, ſeditions; it ſignifies alſo hatred, contempt of the Laws, the neglect of piety, and the incurſions, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines of enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Haly</hi> ſaith, that <hi>quando Luna Eclipſi obruit ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnum, &amp; cooperit eum, morietur Rex Clarus, &amp; magni nominis, in terra occidentis,</hi> but I ſee no reaſon for it: an Eclipſe of the <hi>Sun</hi> would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed have ſignified ſuch a thing, and it is to be feared even in this ſcheame I confeſſe, becauſe the <hi>Sun</hi> is ſomething near the <hi>Dragons taile.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another ſaith, <hi>deſtructionem vini, &amp; multas infirmitates in hominibus, &amp; egritudines, &amp; bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bones ſignificat: magnum caedem inter regem, &amp; vulgus; &amp; multum malum, multas anguſtias, ad
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:120066:32"/>venientes regibus, propter inobedentiam militum corum eis.</hi> Thus in Engliſh it ſignifies an ill vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, many diſeaſes, and infirmities, and buboes; (that is, peſtilentiall or veneriall botches) it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a great ſlaughter between the King, and Commons, and many ſtraits to Kings, by reaſon of the diſobedience of their Souldiers; but M. <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> himſelfe acknowledgeth that the <hi>Moone</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the Parliament; thoſe <hi>Weſtminſterian</hi> or mock-ſun Kings, not true Kings; thoſe that would be Kings, but are not ſo, nor ever ſhall be.</p>
            <p>This Eclipſe happeneth in the ſeventh and eighth houſes of heaven; <hi>quarum ſignificationes ſunt multae interfectiones, &amp; infirmitates, multa bella, &amp; rumores; legum, inſtitutionum, ſectarum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mutationes, multa concupiſcentia in mulieribus miptis, &amp; impregnatio multa.</hi> It ſignifies many ſlaughters, and infirmities, much Wars, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; the changing of Inſtitutions, Lawes, Sects, much concupiſcence in married women, and many great bellies this year.</p>
            <p>This Eclipſe indeed will ſpare none, from the King to the beggar, (eſpecially of the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doners,</hi> or the inhabitants of that City) who have the <hi>Sun, Moone,</hi> mid heaven, or part of fortune, in their nativities, or revolution thereof, or any direction of their principall ſignificators, from 4. degrees to 13. of <hi>Gemini, Sagitarius, Virgo,</hi> or <hi>Piſces;</hi> for it will afflict them one way or other.
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:120066:32"/>Let <hi>London</hi> and Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> beware, for as I am credibly informed, he hath <hi>Gemini</hi> aſcending in his nativity.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> would not have this Eclipſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate till five moneths after it happeneth; but <hi>Origanus</hi> a very good author (one whom I had much rather confide in, then in M. <hi>Lilly</hi>) is of a quite contrary opinion: <hi>viz.</hi> that Eclipſes operate preſently, and M. <hi>Booker</hi> in his Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack for this year, cites him to prove it: <hi>Conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taneum nam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eſt Eclipſes ſtatim operari,</hi> ſaith he, from <hi>Origanus.</hi> If <hi>Origanus</hi> ſaith true (as I beleeve he doth) then am I confident, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore five moneths from the time of the Eclipſe, be run about; Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> himſelf and moſt of that fraternity, muſt prove wandering Planets, ſome to the block, ſome to the gibbet, ſome beyond Sea; and then I hope, if not before, he will be ſo ingenuous as to confeſſe, the preſent working of the influence, of that dire Eclipſe. But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> to be right in this, that the Eclipſe of the <hi>Moone</hi> workes not till five moneths after the time of the Eclipſe, as I know ſome very good authors are of that opinion; it gives them but a little more liberty to repent; it will ſurely fall upon them within nine moneths after the time of the Eclipſe, <hi>viz.</hi> by the end of <hi>Auguſt</hi> next.</p>
            <p>I have finiſhed my judgement of this year: but before I conclude, I muſt needs ſhew you
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:120066:33"/>ſome more of Mr. <hi>Lillies</hi> feinings, and failings; that you may evidently ſee, his Oracles are not of equall authority, with <hi>Sibils,</hi> or old <hi>Merlins;</hi> whoſe ſon he would counterfeit himſelfe; which I might (if I would carpe at very thing he hath done amiſſe) juſtly reckon amongſt his feigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings and ſaylings; but if he be <hi>Merlins</hi> ſon, he is doubtleſſe of a baſtard brood.</p>
            <p>He feigneth that he is a perfct lover of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy,</hi> and of His Majeſty as his Soveraigne; yea he ſaith that it will be a cordiall to his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience when he dies, that he loved <hi>Monarchy:</hi> he now expreſſeth himſelfe to the quick: I hope you doe not thinke that he uſeth to diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, at leaſt not now: but why then doth he affirme, that if the King ſignes the Propoſitions, which went to Him about <hi>February</hi> laſt (as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) he is <hi>mortalium prudentiſſimus?</hi> I doubt not indeed but he wil appeare ſo, and that really to all the world: but how? in not granting them; for if He give away His Kingdome, over whom ſhall He Reigne, over <hi>Canibals</hi> or <hi>Crowes?</hi> If he loves His Majeſty as he pretendeth, why doth he ſo earneſtly deſire the whole Kingdome as one man, to engage againſt all that riſe againſt the Parliament, during the Treaties continuance, yea and after? oh brave Subject! who would thinke indeed but that he loves His Majeſty, ſith he is ſo zealous for His yet captivity? no man can ſerve two maſters (Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi>) comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:120066:33"/>two contrary things; if the King therefore command the Kingdome, (His Kingdome 'tis not the Parliaments) to riſe for His enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the reſtoring unto Him His Crowne, and Dignity, which they violently, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly detaine; if you not onely forbid them ſo to doe, but encourage them to riſe in their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfes, who have done all this and much more againſt Him, who do you then account your Soveraigne? Surely the Parliament, or Army, one of thoſe hopefull ſoules, whom you dubbe with the glorious names, of Senators, States, Cedars, &amp;c. it cannot be King <hi>Charles</hi> you meane, and this will further yet appear: for ſpeaking of the <hi>Treaty,</hi> he ſaith, <hi>that he hopes that His Majeſty now wearied, with the ſad conditions of life, attending Him, and His whole family; and well perceiving the fruitleſſe ſucceſſe of Armes, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for His enlargement, by His friends; will wave ſuch ſtrict Propoſitions, as in former Treaties He might have inſiſted upon;</hi> That is in plaine Engliſh, that he will give away unto the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, His Crowne and Dignity, all but the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, for His enlargement: Oh Traytor, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ropes doeſt thou deſerve? he hopes that His Soveraigne, to whom but now he profeſſed ſo great love, ſo much Allegeance, will un-King Himſelfe, make His adverſaries His Lords, and Soveraignes. This indeed might perhaps pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure His enlargement, bring Him, His Queene
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:120066:34"/>and Progeny, to ſee each other; but how He, She, or They, ſhould ever rejoyce after ſuch an Act, as would abſolutely undoc them all; for my part I can by no meanes imagine. I am ſure and certaine, that His Majeſty hath ever ſhowne Himſelfe moſt inclinable to Peace; yea, hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to buy it, and at a very deare rate: but ſhould a man lay out all his eſtate upon one bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, it had need have be a good peny-worth, or he is quite undone; ſmall hopes of recovery being to be expected from a bankerupt fortune. If Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> had loved His Majeſty, (as he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends) he would never have inſerted into his Booke this following wiſh; <hi>I pray God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that His Majeſty ſtands not too much upon His pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoes of Honour, and that ſafe and ſure Propoſitions may proceed from the Parliament, for the good of us all. His Majesty muſt not ſtand upon ſuch pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoes of Honour, as to have His juſt rights; He muſt be ſurely bound, and is not fit to be truſted;</hi> for this is clearly the ſence of his villanous wiſh. Hath not Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> now ſhewne himſelfe, the moſt notorious feighner, and failer, that ever yet ſet pen to paper?</p>
            <p>He feigneth that the Army is compoſed of more civill and Religious men then ever any Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my was: &amp; dareth any man to contradict if they can, any thing ſaid in their behalf; but he faileth in this alſo, for this is undoubtedly a good axiome, no <hi>Independent</hi> is, or can be an upright man:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:120066:34"/>for therein they imitate the Devil, the firſt <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent</hi> that ever was; and conſequently the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that faction, for he would not depend upon Almighty God, &amp; was therefore throwne downe from heaven to hell, whither all his progeny muſt undoubtedly follow him, if they turne not and repent not in time. I feare <hi>Fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fax,</hi> and the reſt of that crew, will hardly be one day able to pleade his, or their uprightneſſe before God, where (let them be aſſured) they muſt come to a ſtrict account, to anſwer for their great and groſſe abuſes of their Soveraigne his Anointed, contrary to their Allegeance, yea his plighted faith. Oh <hi>England,</hi> if thou well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think'ſt thy ſelfe, thou haſt great cauſe to love theſe men: be ſure if thou takeſt their part, thou muſt partake in their ſufferings. Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> is ſo impudent, as to thinke that no man dares ſpeake againſt them, though they have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ('tis evident to every eye) the greateſt vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies, the groſſeſt impieties, that ever were ſet downe in ſtory: how many widdowes have they made? how many Orphans have they ſlaine? how many Virgins have they deflowred? Oh Godly generation! they cannot erre; elſe I ſhould affirme, that if Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> ſhould rake hell, and skum the Devill ſeaven years together, he could never finde a more curſed crew: would they not have levelled the eſtates of all men? have they not been, and yet are the locuſts and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:120066:35"/>caterpillers that have eat up, and devoured the good things of this Land, and brought it almoſt to an utter deſolation? Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> they that really are hereticks, and ſchiſmatickes, muſt looke to be called ſo to their brazen faces, in ſpight of you copper noſe. Doe you thinke that God delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Colcheſter</hi> to <hi>Fairfax,</hi> or ſubdued the <hi>Scots</hi> by <hi>Cromwell,</hi> for their uprightneſſe? Away you counterfeit, the <hi>Scots</hi> (feare nothing) will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due <hi>Cromwell, Argile</hi> and their confederates, but if need be, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> too will helpe them.</p>
            <p>Another of his ſaylings is this which follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: <hi>I did ever</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>honour thoſe of the</hi> Scots, <hi>who ſtood for a pacification without bloud-ſhed, who were willing to compoſe our differences without an Army:</hi> the others he cals deſpicable fellowes: A brave time when true ſubjects are accounted deſpicable, and Traytors reveren'ſt, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd as Gods darlings. Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> did not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it an Invaſion, when the <hi>Scots</hi> came againſt the King; now he ſaith concerning <hi>Scotland, had not a Divine providence over-powred the Stars, we had not been invaded:</hi> thus to excuſe his owne lying Oracles, he makes himſelfe of Gods coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and ranſacks the very Cabinet of Divinity; Oh how he clawed the <hi>Scots,</hi> when they came for the <hi>Prrliament,</hi> now he wiſhes, that thoſe who pleade the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> civility, or call them <hi>Brethren</hi> to affront the <hi>Parliament;</hi> he wiſheth
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:120066:35"/>
               <hi>Jockey,</hi> and <hi>Moggie,</hi> and all their beggerly brats quartering upon them; but wiſhes are but wind Mr. <hi>Lilly.</hi> 'tis money that buies Land: you could call them <hi>Brethren,</hi> and give them greater and nobler appellations, when they came of your ſide in affront to the <hi>King:</hi> they quartered then upon our etates, and I wiſh heartily, and 'tis but <hi>lex talionis,</hi> that they were now quartered upon your eſtate, and upon the eſtates of ſuch as you are: Their good Angel hath not yet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken them I perceive, as Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> feighneth, how came then <hi>Argile</hi> to be ſo beaten? I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> that you would, but cannot rob them of their good Angel; he refuſeth <hi>to heare the voice of the charmer, charme he never ſo wiſely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wonder Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> in his <hi>Ephemeris,</hi> ſhould highly commend our friends Valliant <hi>Inchequin,</hi> and honourable <hi>Iones</hi> (as he cals them) men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely deſerving: but I am confident, that had he but miſdoubted, that ever they would have declared for the <hi>King,</hi> he would have called them Traytors; Traytors to whom? to thoſe Kingly Rebels, at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But will ſome ſay, is there not truth at all in neither of Mr. <hi>Lillies</hi> bookes? yes, one thing I remember he ſpeakes very truely, for which I hope his great Maſters at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> will ſoundly laſh their Prophet, and that is this: <hi>the Country-man hath great cauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to repine and grumble, having a hard cruell Landlord, Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:120066:36"/>grindes them to powder:</hi> but that you may ſet how loath he is to ſpeake any one truth, except it be at unawares againſt his will; he in the ſame page contradicts it againe: <hi>I ſay</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we muſt adhere to the Parliament and not affront them us of late:</hi> what to ſuch hard cruell Landlords, as grindes them to powder? yes, what though? they are Gods inſtruments; but let me tell you Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> it is an ill cauſe which hath nothing to maintaine it, but lies, forgeries, and perſonall aſperſions.</p>
            <p>There is another thing in his laſt booke, which may be true, but I much fear it; I pray God that the Kingdom may ſee that verified, &amp; then we are happy yet: it is that <hi>the Parliament will willingly condiſcend, to all ſuch things as were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly controverted, and thereby manifeſt to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, their willingneſſe to compoſe differences by a Treaty:</hi> Heavens grant him a true Prophet in this, but if he be I have loſt my marke.</p>
            <p>Thus every judicious man perceives, how mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> hath deluded the Kingdome, with his falſe Oracles, and lying predictions: and yet who bragges ſo much? he boaſts that the Parliament being in low condition, that he peept out the very day of <hi>Nazeby</hi> fight, in his ſtarry meſſenger, and promiſed the routing of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Armies, and their fight into the <hi>Weſt;</hi> he oraggs that he predicted, the integrity of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Nation, in words of length, when the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:120066:36"/>whole Kingdome was much amazed, doubting their integrity: and ſaith, that to their everlaſting honour, they verified his predictions: I beleeve, both theſe are but cracks, ſome of his old feigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and failings; but certaine I am, that to his own everlaſting infamy, &amp; ſome of their immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall honours, they have falſified his predictions this year, although he would very gladly put it off, in his laſt booke, for in that he ſaith, <hi>that he was very doubtfull of them;</hi> but I am certaine, that his booke ſpake this year as confidently for them, as any he wrote, or can poſſibly write: but however, if we grant him to have hit right in theſe predictions; yet <hi>qui inter multa falſa, pauca miſcet vera, non eſt ei in recitando dicta ejus, quic quam tribuendum:</hi> He that amongſt ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lies, tels but now and then a truth, is neither to be regarded, nor beleeved.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Aſtra regunt homines, ſed regit aſtra Deus.</hi>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
